<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The danger of a total and wilful neglect equal to the danger of an unworthy receiving of the Lords Supper wherein as is shewn the nature and danger of an unworthy receiving ... from those words of St. Paul, 1 Corinth. XI. XXIX. by C.P. ...</title>
            <author>Palmer, Charles, 1663?-1734.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1693</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 124 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 43 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A54864</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing P221</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R32975</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12803116</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12803116</idno>
            <idno type="VID">94102</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A54864)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 94102)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1037:10)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The danger of a total and wilful neglect equal to the danger of an unworthy receiving of the Lords Supper wherein as is shewn the nature and danger of an unworthy receiving ... from those words of St. Paul, 1 Corinth. XI. XXIX. by C.P. ...</title>
                  <author>Palmer, Charles, 1663?-1734.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 69 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by J.A. for Tho. Parkhurst ... and are to be sold by Obed. Smith ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1693.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Attributed by Wing to Charles Palmer.</note>
                  <note>Imperfect: pages cropped, faded, with loss of print.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Cambridge University Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Church of England --  Customs and practices.</term>
               <term>Lord's Supper --  Sermons.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-08</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-09</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-10</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-10</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:94102:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE DANGER OF A Total and Wilful NEGLECT Equal to the DANGER of an UNWORTHY RECEIVING OF THE <hi>Lords Supper,</hi> WHEREIN As is ſhewn the Nature and Danger of an Unworthy Receiving, ſo the great Folly and Sin of Neglecting it.</p>
            <p>From thoſe Words of St. <hi>Paul,</hi> 1 CORINTH. XI. xxix.</p>
            <p>By <hi>C. P.</hi> A. M.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>J. A.</hi> for <hi>Tho. Parkhurſt</hi> at the <hi>Bible and Three Crowns</hi> at the Lower End of <hi>Cheap-ſide</hi> near <hi>Mercer's Chappel,</hi> and are to be ſold by <hi>Obed. Smith</hi> Bookſeller at <hi>Daventry</hi> in <hi>Northamptonſhire,</hi> 1693.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:94102:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:94102:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>TO THE READER.</head>
            <p>HOwever unneceſſary this Enſuing Diſcourſe may ſeem to be in the Judgment of ſome, by rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of thoſe many excellent and full Diſcourſes that have been already pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhed concerning the Sacrament of the Lord's Supper, and which almoſt render it impoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible to publiſh any thing New upon this Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject:</p>
            <p>Yet I am not without ſome hopes of its do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Good, if not to thoſe whoſe Circumſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces will not permit them to buy and peruſe the ſeveral Treatiſes that are now Extant con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the Lords Supper; yet to my own Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhioners, for whoſe ſake it is chiefly publiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and who indeed ſtand in need of Line up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on Line, to bring them to a Practical Appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>benſion of the Obligation that lyeth upon Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians
<pb facs="tcp:94102:3"/>to the Receiving of the Lords Supper, as well as to the worthy Approach thereof: And if in any Inſtance this Diſcourſe may pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure the End for which it was deſign'd, and do good to them, or any Perſons elſe; as I ſhall be thankful to God for it, ſo ſhall I look up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on it as no mean Reward, whatever Cenſures it meets with from others.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:94102:3"/>
            <head>THE DANGER OF A Total and Wilful NEGLECT Equal to the Danger of an UNWORTHY RECEIVING Of the <hi>Lord's Supper,</hi>
            </head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>1 COR. XI.</hi> ch. <hi>29.</hi> v.</bibl>
                  <p>For he that eateth and drinketh Unworthily, eateth and drinketh Damnation to himſelf, not diſcerning the Lord's Body.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>AMongſt other the Reaſons that are urg'd for the Forbearance from the Sacrament of the Lords Supper, the ſenſe of the greatneſs of the Ordinance, and the ſad Sentence that is declar'd againſt Unworthy Receivers, is urg'd as a great Barr by ſome Men thereto.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="2" facs="tcp:94102:4"/>
Too many indeed are the Excuſes that Men make for their not Coming to this Heavenly Feaſt; but that which is moſt prevalent with well mean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing People, is the Fears of their own Unfitneſs for it, and the Doubts that they never ſhall be Worthy.</p>
            <p>Now for the ſatisfaction of ſuch Men it is that I have made Choice of the Words of St. <hi>Paul,</hi> as the Subject of the following Diſcourſe, and from them ſhall Treat of the following things.</p>
            <list>
               <item>1. What is here meant by Eating and Drink<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Unworthily.</item>
               <item>2. Upon what Account, and by what Ways Men receive the Sacrament of the Lords Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per Unworthily, or are Unworthy Commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicants, and by what they are not.</item>
               <item>3. In what Senſe the Receiving of it Unworthi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly is ſo dangerous as it is ſaid to be in the Text.</item>
               <item>4. That although it be very Dangerous to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive the Sacrament of the Lords Supper Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthily, yet the Total and Wilfull Neglect thereof is as dangerous; and that the not partaking of other Ordinances Worthily, makes Men liable to Damnation, as well as the not partaking of the Sacrament Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thily.</item>
               <item>5. I ſhall Cloſe all with an Exhortation.</item>
            </list>
            <p n="1">1. Of the Firſt, What is here Meant by Eating and Drinking Unworthily.</p>
            <p>Now by Eating and Drinking Unworthily, not only the Words foregoing limit the Application of them to the Receiving of the Lord's Supper Unworthily, but the general Apprehenſion of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians that they are to be ſo taken, do declare the
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:94102:4"/>ſame. It's true indeed, that the Words are <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> of our common Eating and Drinking, that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> ſoever Eateth or Drinketh Unworthily, that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> ther abuſeth God's good Creatures, or himſelf <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> an Unworthy or Intemperate Uſe of them, E<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="4 letters">
                  <desc>••••</desc>
               </gap>eth and Drinketh Damnation to himſelf, without Repentance, his Gluttony and Exceſs, as u<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> thankfulneſs for God's good Creatures, being Sins<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> that make him lyable to the Wrath of God.</p>
            <p>But yet as all eating and drinking is not a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiving of a Sacrament; ſo not of that which is a Commemorative Ordinance of Chriſt's Body and Blood, being given and ſhed for us, for elſe we might ſay that Heathens or Infidels receive the Sacrament when they eat and drink: But as this is inconſiſtent with the Notions that men have of the Sacrament; ſo particularly with the ſcope of the Apoſtles words, which is concerning eat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and drinking, according to the Inſtitution of our Saviour, in remembrance of his Death and Paſſion, and agreeably hereto he tells, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11. <hi>ch. v.</hi> 26. That <hi>as oft as ye eat this Bread and drink this Cup, ye do ſhew the Lords Death till he comes;</hi> and in my Text, <hi>He that eateth and drinketh unworthily, eateth and drinketh damnation:</hi> But why? it follows, becauſe he <hi>diſcerns not the Lords Body,</hi> of which he then Sacramentally partakes, as to the outward Symbols or Elements thereof.</p>
            <p>But why do I ſtand to ſhew, that by eating and drinking here, is meant the receiving of the Lord's Supper, and not common Eating at our ordinary Meals: Since tho' ſome prophane Perſons to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſe themſelves in their abſence from this Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance pretend that they can receive the Sacrament as oft as they eat and drink; yet all ſober Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians do apply the words of the Apoſtle to the Sacrament of the Lord's Supper, and their Doubts
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:94102:5"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="3" facs="tcp:94102:5"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="4" facs="tcp:94102:6"/>are not ſo much what is here meant by eating and drinking, as what the doing it ſo unworthily ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifies, which is the next thing to be ſpoke to.</p>
            <p>NOW, by Eating and Drinking unworthily, is not meant, a not deſerving, or not being worthy to eat and drink what we do at the Lord's Supper, as Deſerving, or being Worthy, ſignifies our de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſert or merit to partake of what we there partake; (for in this ſenſe all are unworthy, yea even the Apoſtles were ſo; yea in that we come to this Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinance to commemorate the Sufferings of Chriſt, as having laid down his Life for our Sins, we do hereby ſhew, That we of our ſelves are not worthy to receive ſo great a Favour, as the pardon of our Sins, and other benefits of his Sufferings, but only by his Merits:) But tho we are not worthy in this ſenſe, ſo as to deſerve a partaking of what we there partake; yet ſuch is the Goodneſs of God, that if we are but ſincere in our preparations, in our Repentance, Thankfulneſs, and the like, as alſo in our Reſolutions and Actions of Faith, Love and Obedience, God will accept of us as worthy in a Goſpel ſenſe, and bleſs his Ordinance unto us.</p>
            <p>Such an Unworthineſs then as the not deſerving the Favours we then receive, is not the unworthi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs ſpoken of in the Text, ſince there are none that are ſo worthy in themſelves, no, not even St. <hi>Paul;</hi> and therefore I proceed to ſhew what is the unworthineſs ſpoken of in this place.</p>
            <p>Now by Eating and Drinking unworthily, I pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſume is meant, a performing the Duty of receiving the Lords Supper in ways unbecoming, unſuitable, or unfit to the Nature and Deſign of it, it is to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive it otherwiſe than we ought, or not agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ably to the worth of it, or the eſteem we ought to bear to it. This I take to be the meaning of un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthily, and with this the <hi>Corinthians</hi> were charg'd,
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:94102:6"/>as alſo ſuffer'd for, when they made no difference betwixt the Lord's Body, and their Common meals, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>t came to, and behaved themſelves thereat diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>orderly, as you may ſee Verſe 21 of this Chapter.</p>
            <p>And ſo I paſs over to the next thing I propoſed to treat of, <hi>viz.</hi> Upon what account, and by what ways men receive the Sacrament of the Lords Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per unworthily, or are unworthy Communicants. Now this they do, as they either come unprepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to, or behave themſelves diſorderly or unſuita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ly thereat.</p>
            <p>And firſt, Men eat and drink unworthily at the Lord's Supper, when they come unprepar'd to it; and then are they ſaid to be unprepar'd, when they <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ome not with thoſe Conditions or Qualifications which belong to him that is a Worthy Receiver, and ſo accordingly as men are wanting thereof, more or leſs, they may be ſaid to be more or leſs <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>repar'd, I ſhall therefore ſpeak ſomething con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terning theſe Qualifications.</p>
            <p>And firſt, One Qualification of a Worthy Receiv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, or Communicant, is a competent knowledge of the Nature and End of this Ordinance, which if Men come to the Sacrament without, they eat and drink unworthily. Before People eat of this Bread, and drink of this Cup, they ought to examine them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.28. and as of other things, ſo of their Knowledge, what is to be done at the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment: And if upon Enquiry they find they have <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ot any Knowledge to diſtinguiſh it from other <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ating and drinking, when they do not diſcern <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>he Lord's Body, they eat and drink unworthily, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s it is in the Text: And how indeed can any Man <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>o a thing worthily, that knows not what he doth, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>or why he doth it? And agreeable hereto are <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>he words of the Learned Biſhop <hi>Taylor,</hi> 
               <q>That he that knows nothing of the Sacrament, nor
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:94102:7"/>can be taught any thing, muſt be permitted to the Mercies of God, and the Prayers of the Church, but he hath not to do with the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion.</q> See Bp. <hi>Taylor</hi>'s <hi>Worthy Communicant,</hi> Chap. 3. Sect. 3.</p>
            <p>But as to this Qualification of a Competent Knowledge, there are but few but what do, o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> may come with it, if it be not their own faults; for he that hath but ſo mach Learning as to be able to read the Bible, wherein the Inſtitution and End of it are ſo clearly laid down; as alſo any of thoſe Books about the Sacrament which are publiſhed amongſt us, that either knows his Catechiſm, or ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plies himſelf to the hearing of God's Word, and withall hath but the common Reaſon and Under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding of a Man; it is his own fault if he doth no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> attain to ſome knowledge of that Ordinance. Its true, that all have not the like Knowledge, no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> are they equally skill'd in the Myſteries of Faith; and as there is not alike Knowledge in all, ſo nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther is it requir'd it ſhould be ſo, there being new<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>born Babes as well as grown Perſons in Chriſt: So that if Men have but a competent knowledge, ſo much as makes them ſenſible of the Nature and End of this Duty, and what they are to do at, and after, as well as before it, their Knowledge ſhall be reckon'd ſufficient.</p>
            <p>Nay even amongſt the leſs knowing, but ſincere Chriſtians, it many times happens, that tho' they cannot define the Notion of the Sacrament, no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> talk ſo Learnedly about it as the <hi>Learned Ones</hi> do<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> they may yet be more worthy in God's ſight, and more experimentally find out the ſweetneſs of this Ordinance than the others: And tho' they can't diſpute ſo much concerning the manner of Chriſt's preſence as the great Caſuiſts do, they may ye<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> be in a cloſer Communion with him, and from the
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:94102:7"/>ſenſe of Chriſt's Love diſplay'd to them in this Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinance, have their Hearts ſo enlarg'd that they can even dye for him.</p>
            <p>But if after all, ſome are ſo ignorant in this Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and that wilfully too, in the midſt of ſuch Preaching and Printing as we enjoy, That they <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>now not what the receiving of the Sacrament means, and why it was ordain'd, I conclude they ought not to come; or if they do, they come un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthily, becauſe they diſcern not the Lords Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>y.</p>
            <p>But Secondly, Another Qualiſication of a Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy Receiver, (without which if men come, they <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ome unprepar'd, and ſo eat and drink unworthi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly) is a real and hearty deſire to the Ordinance <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>d the Benefits of it; for how can Men receive that worthily or ſuitably to the Nature and End thereof, that do not deſire it? He therefore that would not eat and drink unworthily, muſt alſo <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>amine his deſires; doth he deſire to have his <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ins pardoned, and Chriſt dwell in him? Is he <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>illing to take on him Chriſt's Nature, and to be <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ne with him? or is he glad to be in Covenant <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ith God? In ſhort, doth he deſire Chriſt upon the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>erms that Chriſt is propos'd? If he doth, he is <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>a fair way of being a good Communicant, yea, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> is one that is bidden and invited to come, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>ch.</hi> 1 <hi>v.</hi> But on the other hand, if a Man comes <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> it without any deſire, or mind to it, and had ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>er not partake of it, (was he left at his liberty) <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>t only from fear to ſtay away, or from worldly engagements to come, he frequents it, it is not <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> be thought that he will be a Worthy Receiver, becauſe in ſuch addreſſes a Man comes to it without <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>is Heart, and ſo for want thereof his Devotion <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>d Behaviour is like to be but lukewarm, if not <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ld or dead.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="8" facs="tcp:94102:8"/>
If indeed a Man comes to this Ordinance to en<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> creaſe his Deſires after it, if he comes not only upon the ſenſe of his Duty to come, but out o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> hopes that by coming his Heart will be enlarg'd to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards Chriſt, and he become more fit for this Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinance: If he, I ſay, deſires that he may deſire Chriſt more, and is truly ſorrowful that he is no more deſirous, this ſhews the ſincerity of his Heart in what he doth, and conſequently that he is no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> unworthy in God's Merciful acceptance of what he doth, tho he hath not thoſe paſſionate heats, o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ſree Enlargements of Soul as ſome have. But i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> on the other hand, our coming to this Ordinance be a Burden to us, and we deſire (if it may be <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> to be excuſed; but becauſe we are not excus'd therefore only yield a formal and outward re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect, we don't deal worthily by it when we ea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> and drink at Chriſt's Supper with no Appetite<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> and do as it were diſlike, tho' we feed on the Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments thereof.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, Another Qualification, without which if Men come, they are unprepar'd for the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and ſo eat and drink unworthily, is Repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, or a ſincere Reſolution of amendment. An<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> truly they that come to this, or to any other O<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinance without Repentance, or Reſolutions o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Amendment, come unworthily; and accordingly God tells us of the Wicked, that their Sacrific<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>is an abomination to him,</hi> Prov. 15.8. That his <hi>Fa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> is ſet againſt them that do evil,</hi> that he will not hea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> their Prayers, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 1.13, 15. yea, all their action of Devotion and Worſhip are loathſome in h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> ſight, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 66. <hi>ch.</hi> v. 3. And if ſo, you may ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gine they are not in ſuch Caſes worthily perform'd when they are ſo hateful to God: and now, if that the living in Sin marrs the Duty, as well as hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders the bleſſing of other Ordinances, will it n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="9" facs="tcp:94102:8"/>alſo render us unworthy Communicants: Surely if living in Sin makes us unworthy in Prayer, it will much more do ſo in the Sacrament, ſo that Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance is a neceſſary Qualification for the Receiv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the Lord's Supper. As to Repentance, what it is, and how much it contains a change of Heart and practice; or at leaſt a ſincere endeavour to evidence our inward Change by our outward Acts, ſo much as we have Opportunity and Abili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, I think I need not ſtand now to ſhew, it being ſo oft treated of by others, and hath been ſo large<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly handled in my Pariſh, for the good of which <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>his Diſcourſe is primarily intended; but ſhall proceed to ſhew, how the want thereof in any <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>an makes him an unworthy Communicant, for ſo long as he retains his Sins, he retains that which is an Enemy to Chriſt, and caus'd him to ſuffer; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ea, that which diſhonours not only him, but his Ordinance too, which is an Ordinance of Purity, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nd therefore to be receiv'd with Purity; and conſequently if he doth not drive Chriſt away from his Ordinance, yet by his Sins he puts a ſtop to any Fellowſhip that he may expect with Chriſt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hereby, there being no Communion with Light <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nd Darkneſs, nor hath Chriſt and <hi>Belial</hi> any Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ord, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 6.14, 15. for to bring our Sins un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>orrow'd for before him, what is it elſe than to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ring his Enemies before him, and own our Friend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hip with them, and conſequently to affront him? And now we muſt needs think, that ſince they <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ere the Sins of Men which made him ſuffer ſo <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>uch, he can't well bear the ſight of them in his <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>reſence, and eſpecially as allovv'd by them, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ho for his ſake as well as their own have ſuch <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ogent reaſons eternally to hate and forfake them. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> ſhort, ſince the very end of this Ordinance is to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ommemorate Chriſt's dying for our Sins, and to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vey
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:94102:9"/>the benefit of his Blood, which was ſhed for the remiſſion of them, it can't but be an unwo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> thy return, to bring our Sins before him unrepent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed of.</p>
            <p>But why do I ſtand to prove, that Repentance is a Qualification of a Worthy Communicant, ſince even Wicked Men themſelves own that it is ſo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> and therefore make ſome pretences to it before they approach to the Lord's Table, yea, the ſenſe o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> their coming thereto ſhall put them into ſom<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> good Moods, and faint reſolutions of Amendment <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> nay it may be cauſe them to ſet a day or two a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> part beforehand, to bethink themſelves to rea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ſome good Books, or with <hi>Ahab</hi> to go ſoftly and look mournfully.</p>
            <p>Yet after all, here lyes the tryal of our Prepa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ration and Worthineſs in this Point, whether ou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Reſolutions be ſincere, entire, or conſtant, and w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> are become new Men in Heart and practice too, a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> far as we have made tryal of our Change; whe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ther our Sorrow for Sin is like to laſt longer tha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> the Communion day, and we are like to be goo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> after as well as before the Sacrament; for if w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> make never ſo good Reſolutions, and ſpend a day or two before the Sacrament never ſo well in Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligious Exerciſes, and yet when we have Communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cated return to our old ways, if we find that th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> bent and inclination of our Soul is not alter'd, and our zeal againſt Sin is only Temporary and for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mal, we do not eat and drink worthily, but un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthily, and for all our outward Communica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, Chriſt may ſay of us as he did of <hi>Judas, Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold, the hand of him that betrayeth me, is with me o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> the Table.</hi> Luk. 22.21.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, Another Qualification of a Worth<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Communicant, without which, if Men come to th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Sacrament they are unprepar'd, and ſo eat and
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:94102:9"/>drink unworthily, is Charity: Now by Charity I mean not only a Love to God, but Love and for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giveneſs to Men.</p>
            <p>And <hi>Firſt,</hi> As Charity ſignifies a Love to God, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e that comes to the Sacrament without it, can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not receive it worthily; for how can a Man have ſuch a due ſenſe of Chriſt's Love in this Ordinance <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s he ought, and yet remain without Love to him? Nay, if he is ſenſible of Chriſt's Love, and will <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ot Love him again, the more unworthy he, that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ill not do ſo much as the <hi>Publicans,</hi> who love hoſe that love them, <hi>Mat.</hi> 6.46. Yea very un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grateful, and ſo unworthy is he, that is going to receive the Pledges of Chriſt's Love, and that of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>is dying and greateſt Love, (for greater Love <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ath no Man than to lay down his Life for his friends, except it be a laying of it down for his <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>emies, for this is Love beyond compariſon, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>et ſuch Love did Chriſt ſhew when he laid down <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s Life for Sinners;) <hi>For a good man peradventure <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>me would even dare to dye: but God com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ded his love to us, in that whilſt we were <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> Sinners, Chriſt dyed for us.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rom. 4. <hi>v.</hi> 7, 8.</note> And now <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hen God hath ſo loved us, we cannot <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>y we are worthy to partake of his Love, if we <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ll not love him that hath endured ſo much for <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>r ſakes.</p>
            <p>In ſhort, the very Sacrament it ſelf is an Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nance of Love; it is a diſplaying of Chriſts in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>mparable Love in dying for Sinners under Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>amental Repreſentations: If therefore we will <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>t let our Love bear a part in the Solemnities thereof, we are unworthy of it, Love being not <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ly a preparative Duty, but an Ornamental as <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ell as Active Grace therein, But</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly,</hi> As Love to God is ſuch a Qualificati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>, without which, if Men come to the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:94102:10"/>they come unprepar'd, and ſo eat and drink unworthily, ſo alſo is Charity and For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giveneſs to Men: Now by Charity to Men, I mean not only a forbearance of Revenge, but a doing of good to thoſe that ſtand in need of it: And truly unleſs a Man can come in Charity, he comes but to his hurt; not that the want of Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity is an excuſe for our Abſence from this Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance, but a doubling of our guilt, in that we ſtay away upon ſo ſinful account, but yet when we come without Charity, we come unſuitably to it, becauſe this is an Ordinance of Charity —It is by this Ordinance that we are made Friends with God, and it is by this that we ſhould be Friends one with another, that as we are Members of the ſame Body, ſo we become Members one of another, and conſequently ſhould not hurt or devour one ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther: What? when we feaſt on the Memorials of the greateſt Love, when we are not only invited to be reconciled to God, but have ſuch a Pattern of Love and Kindneſs before us in his dying even to ſave us, can we yet be Uncharitable and Cruel? One Man beareth hatred againſt another, and yet doth he ſeek for pardon from the Lord; if he that is but fleſh nouriſheth hatred, who will en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treat for the pardon of his Sins? could even the Son of <hi>Sirac</hi> tell us long ago, <hi>Ecclus.</hi> 28. <hi>v.</hi> 2, 3, 4. But a greater than he hath told us, that we muſt firſt be <hi>reconciled to our Brother,</hi> in Affections at leaſt, before we come with our <hi>Gift to the Altar<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Mat.</hi> 5.23, 24, 25. And again, if we forgive no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Men their Treſpaſſes, neither will our heavenly Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther forgive us ours, <hi>Mat.</hi> 6.15. and many ſuch Texts there are to the like purpoſe; nay, from the ſenſe of Chriſt's dying Love, we find Chriſt exhorting his Diſciples to the love of each other yea in keeping this Ordinance, St. <hi>Paul</hi> exhorts th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="13" facs="tcp:94102:10"/>
               <hi>Corinthians,</hi> that they ſhould not keep this Feaſt with the Leven of Malice, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.8.</p>
            <p>And now forgiveneſs and Charity, being ſo much requir'd at our hands, can we think to become Worthy Communicants without it? No: he who hates his Brother, whatever his hopes and preten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces are, is but a Murderer, and ye know that no Murderer, till he repents, is a fit Gueſt for the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and merciful Jeſus; yea, St. <hi>John</hi> by way of In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terrogation, implying a denyal, asks How it can be, that the Love of God can dwell in him, who when he hath this World's goods, and ſeeth the needs of his Brother, yet ſhuts up his Bowels of Compaſſion from him? 1 <hi>John</hi> 3.17. Nay if Chriſt declares, that ſuch as will not give Meat to the Hungry, and Drink to the Thirſty,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 25. <hi>v.</hi> 41.</note> ſhall depart from him, and are not worthy of his preſence, but ſit only for the Devil and his Angels, it is hard to think how he will ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept of the unmerciful and cruel Perſon, as a fit Gueſt at the Heavenly Feaſt, at this Ordinance of Forgiveneſs and Charity.</p>
            <p>In ſhort, a very wicked Servant is he, and no Friend of Chriſt's, who tho' he comes to entreat for the forgiveneſs of ten thouſand Talents, doth at the ſame time keep a reſolution of exacting the pence of his Brother; ſurely if the Love and Pity that is due to his Brother will not move him, the Conſideration of what a Motive it is to his own Forgiveneſs from God, that he forgives others, ſhould even make him more kind for his own as well as others ſake, which if he is not, we muſt needs own, he is an unwelcome Gueſt, when he is of ſo contrary Behaviour to the Doctrine and Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample of Chriſt, which to be of, as it is offenſive to him at all times, ſo much more in the midſt of the Memorials of his Love and Good will, as well
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:94102:11"/>as Gods Forgiveneſs to us, through the Merits of his Son. Thus neceſſary is Forgiveneſs to make us worthy Communicants, as well as it is the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition of God to us.</p>
            <p>But now leaſt Perſons ſhould miſtake the Nature of Forgiveneſs, tho' few or none there are but what will own the Duty of it; before I leave this Qualification, I ſhall endeavour to ſhew you what is meant by Forgiveneſs, and what is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quir'd of us thereby. As,</p>
            <p n="1">1. By Forgiveneſs, is not meant a bare Decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration thereof, or a praying to God to forgive thoſe that have wronged us; but an actual for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giving, a doing what we ſay, and a Heartineſs in our deſires: Yea it contains the laying aſide the thoughts of doing another Miſchief, as well as the forbearance of a revengeful Act; for he that thinks and wiſhes ill to another, ſhews that he hath Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lice in his Heart, tho he forbears to execute it. Yea, he that dares not do another a miſchief, but yet deſires God to be his Revenger, according to his Imaginations, doth in that ſhew, it is fear or ſomething elſe, that reſtrains his hand, but his Heart is revengefull, and it ſhews that he would revenge if he might, and ſo cannot be ſaid to for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>give. But,</p>
            <p n="2">2. By Forgiveneſs is not only meant a forbear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance of revenging an Injury, but a Forgetfulneſs of the Injury too, ſo far as to ceaſe from revenge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full thoughts or Expreſſions.</p>
            <p>For he that remembers a wrong done him, ſo as to heighten his Paſſion under a new Provoca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; he doth not heartily forgive, in that he keeps the ſeed of the paſt Anger and Paſſion ſtill lurk<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing within him.</p>
            <p>It's true where a man hath done me wrong, I may remember it ſo ſar, as to take care to avoyd
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:94102:11"/>the like or any other from him for the future; yet tho' by way of Caution and Prevention, a man may remember a paſt offence, the better to arm and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend himſelf; he is not ſo to remember it, as to make it an addition to his reſolutions of Revenge, upon a ſecond Offence; for indeed ſo to do, is not to put out the Fire, but only to cover it in Aſhes. But,</p>
            <p n="3">3. By Forgiveneſs is not only meant, an act or ſtate of Inoffenſiveneſs towards others, a forbear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance of revenging an Injury, and a forgetfulneſs of it ſo far as to ceaſe from revengeful thoughts or Expreſſions; but alſo a readineſs to ſhew acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of Civility and Kindneſs ſo far as they are due from us, even to thoſe that treſpaſs againſt us.</p>
            <p>It's true indeed, I am not obliged to exerciſe thoſe particular acts of Friendſhip with him, from whom I have received Injuries, and am ſtill like to receive more, from the ill will and deſigns he hath againſt me; nor doth the Duty of Forgive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs exclude our Endeavours after ſatisfaction in a juſt and legal way: Yet ſo far doth Forgiveneſs require our Love and Kindneſs to Offenders againſt us, that they are not to be excluded our Prayers, or our Acts of Kindneſs to them as they are men, tho' we can't own them as Friends. Even to our worſt Enemies we muſt do that Good that we would do to all men, as men; (that is) we muſt not only forbear to deal unjuſtly or cruelly with them, but ſhew them all the Kindneſs that God by the Goſpel, and common Rules of Society and Civility hath made it our Duty to ſhew; and eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially where there is no reaſon to the contrary, but we may do the ſame things for them as well as others; tho they have offended us, we muſt not ſee them ſtarve, nor periſh for want of our Relief, for ſo the Apoſtle tells us: If even <hi>thine Enemy hunger, feed him; if he thirſt, give him drink;</hi> yea,
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:94102:12"/>where we may, we are to <hi>overcome</hi> his <hi>evil with</hi> our <hi>good,</hi> Rom. 12.20, 21.</p>
            <p>And thus I have ſhewn in ſeveral of the Quali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fications of a worthy Receiver or Communicant, <hi>viz.</hi> 1. Knowledge of the Nature and End of the Sacrament of the Lords Supper. 2. A real and hearty deſire to this Ordinance, and the Benefits of it. 3. Repentance or ſincere Reſolution of a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendment. 4. Charity and Forgiveneſs: That if men come without them, they are unprepared for the Sacrament, and ſo eat and drink unworthily. And indeed beſides theſe Qualifications of a wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy Communicant, there are others without which if we come to the Sacrament, we eat and drink unworthily; ſuch as Faith and Thankfulneſs to our Saviour for the Pledges of his Love. But theſe being Graces that are chiefly exerciſed at the Lords Supper, I ſhall ſpeak of them under the ſecond way which I inſtanced, whereby men re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive the Sacrament of the Lords Supper unwor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thily, <hi>viz.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>2d. Way.</hi> When they behave themſelves diſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derly or unſuitably at it. Now men may be ſaid to behave themſelves diſorderly or unſuitably, when they don't ſhew a due reſpect to what they are doing; but either allow their Hearts to hanker as well as their thoughts to wander after the World or Sin, or are prophane in their behaviour at it: Nay I may ſafely ſay, they don't deal with it very worthily, that either look upon their Receiving it to be little more than a common or ordinary Eat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing or Drinking, or elſe undervalue the Bread and Wine, as but of little uſe and purpoſe.</p>
            <p>It's true the Bread and Wine are but Creatures as our Church terms them, they are but Bread and Wine in their Nature, but yet as they are inſtituted by Chriſt, to be received in remembrance of hi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="17" facs="tcp:94102:12"/>Death and Paſſion, the taking of them according to Chriſt's Inſtitution, is a Symbol, or Sacrament of our taking and eating the Body and Blood of Chriſt, and therefore as they are appointed by Chriſt, we are not to undervalue them, by think<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing we may as well receive Chriſt and the benefits of the New Covenant without them as with them, when yet we have opportunity and invitations thereto, which indeed to undervalue, is not only to undervalue the Elements, but the Wiſdom and Authority of the Inſtituter.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Thoſe Men may be ſaid to behave themſelves diſorderly and unſuitably at the Sacrament, and ſo receive it unworthily, that receive it without Faith: This Sacrament being ſuch an Ordinance, that without Faith it cannot be received, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it is the Apoſtles Advice, that we ſhould draw nigh it with <hi>full aſſurance of Faith,</hi> Heb. 10.22. for indeed Faith is not only the hand to lead us unto Chriſt, <hi>Heb.</hi> 11.6, 7. but of applying Chriſt unto us, and making that which was done for ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, <hi>Mat.</hi> 26.28. to be effectually conveyed unto us, for what doth it ſignifie for me to Commemo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate the ſnfferings of a dying Saviour by receiving Bread and Wine according to Chriſt's Appoint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, If I have not Faith, that the benefits there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of belong to me, or cannot ſpiritually feed upon his Body and Blood by Faith, it being by Faith that we feed upon him? for as to the Corporeal eating of his Body and Blood, it is ſuch a thing, that could the Papiſts quit their Avowance of, and yet keep up the Authority and pretended Infallibility of their Church, many Learned Men think they could eaſily part with their Opinion or Belief thereof: However, if it is the Doctrine of the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> it is not the Doctrine of Chriſt, ſuch being not only contrary to Senſe and
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:94102:13"/>Reaſon, but to Faith alſo; for as to Faith, we are told in <hi>Heb.</hi> 11. <hi>v.</hi> 1. it <hi>is the Evidence of things not ſeen.</hi> Now if Chriſt be Corporeally preſent, if the Bread that we eat be the very ſubſtantial Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy of Chriſt, it is then ſeen, and ſo our Faith be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing an Evidence of what is ſeen, it is not the true Faith, in that it is contrary to the definition of it. Nay further, this Sacrament ceaſeth to be a Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament, which is to be an outward and a Viſible Sign of ſome Inward and Spiritual thing, if ſo be that after Conſecration the Bread and Wine be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come the Body and Blood of Chriſt in a Corpore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al ſence, there then remaining no outward Sign or Sacrament.</p>
            <p>But however, the Papiſts are ſo quick-ſighted to ſee ſuch a Corporeal Preſence of our Saviour, it is more than we can, or more than I read that the Apoſtles ſaw in the Bread and Wine of which he ſpeaks, when he ſaith, <hi>This is my Body, this is my Blood,</hi> when at the ſame time they ſaw his Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy ſeparate from the Bread he gave them, and they plainly diſcerned that when the Cup of Wine was given them, his Blood was not then ſhed.</p>
            <p>It's true, That Faith ſees that in the Sacrament which Reaſon doth not; but yet tho' Reaſon ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mits to Faith, yet Faith doth not put out our Sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes from being Judges where they may, as they may be in diſcerning what is Fleſh and Blood, and what is Bread and Wine.</p>
            <p>But if any Man will ſay, that our Senſes are not to be uſed in Matters of Faith, I think he ſpeaks very raſh, when even Chriſt appeal'd to the Sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes of his Apoſtles to confirm their Belief of what he ſaid, that he was the ſame Chriſt (tho riſen again) that was Crucified, <hi>Luk.</hi> 24.39. Since there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the eating of Chriſt's Body and Blood, tho real, is Spiritual and Sacramental, it remains,
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:94102:13"/>that what we ſee and taſte of him at the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, is by Faith, which Faith conſiders not ſo much how the Elements feed the Body, as how the things repreſented, ſealed and apply'd in this Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinance, feed and nouriſh the Soul. And indeed it is by this, that we not only view him hanging up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Croſs, and ſhedding his Blood, but Feaſt our ſelves of him, that we may dwell in him, and he in us: If therefore we come withour Faith, we are unworthy of this Ordinance, yea, we Eva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuate it as to our ſelves.</p>
            <p>But then here let us not be miſtaken in our No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Faith, or think that a bare and true belief of Chriſt's Preſence and Bleſſings in this Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance is the right Belief for it; No, but the Faith of a good Communicant is a Goſpel Faith, ſuch a Faith as receives Chriſt according to the Terms propos'd to us in the Goſpel, and the Sacrament alſo.</p>
            <p>Now that which is ſo, receives him not only as one ſhedding his Blood, and giving his Body to ſave Men from the Guilt and Puniſhment of Sin, but from Sin it ſelf, it is ſuch as receives him as a King to rule us, as well as pardon and ſave us; yea, it receives Chriſt's Body and Blood, that our Bodies may be made clean, and our Souls waſh'd thereby, yea, in Chriſt Jeſus the Faith that avails is a working Faith, it works by Love, <hi>Gal.</hi> 5.6. and it works by Thankfulneſs too: And therefore in the third place,</p>
            <p n="3">3. Thoſe Men may be ſaid to behave themſelves diſorderly and unſuitably at the Sacrament, and ſo receive it unworthily, that receive it without Thankfulneſs. The very Buſineſs and Nature of it declares, that it is a Thankful Memorial of the dying Love of Chriſt, or a ſhewing forth of his Death, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.26. So that by no means can
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:94102:14"/>they receive it worthily that do not receive it thank<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully. And how indeed can we but be thankful, if we conſider what we do and receive in this Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance; we feaſt upon the Memorials of his laying down his Life for Sinners, yea, for ſuch Sinners as our ſelves, and that in our ſtead, to expiate for our Tranſgreſſions, and deliver us from the Wrath of God, and the ſad Conſequ ents of it; and now are we Worthy Remembrancers of his Love, when we are not thankful? Suppoſe we ſee a Man ready to ſtarve, yea a Man ready to be overwhelm'd with the Waves of the Sea, and in each of theſe Caſes receiving relief and Succour, wou'd not he (do ye think) be thankful? yea, unworthy would he be if he would not be thankful for ſuch Bleſſings.</p>
            <p>And now when we are call'd to Feaſt at this Heavenly Banquet upon this Bread from Heaven, and Food of Saints, yea, upon the Repreſentatives and Seals of God's Eternal Love in Chriſt towards Sinners, that deſerve, yea, that are ready to periſh, ſhall not we be thankful? Nay, do but conſider, who it was that hath done all this? What it was he ſuffered, and how much, and ſee whether we can Commemorate this his Love, and not be thankful? And truly if we can, without being ſo, it is a ſign of a hard as well as ungrateful Heart, and is very unſuitable to the Nature and Deſign of this Ordinance, which is ſo much an Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance of Thankſgiving and Praiſe, that from thence it takes one of its Names, and is call'd the <hi>Euchariſt,</hi> or Thankſgiving.</p>
            <p>And thus have I at large ſhewn upon what Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count, and by what ways Men receive the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the Lords Supper unworthily, <hi>viz.</hi> when they come unprepar'd to, or behave themſelves diſorderly or unſuitably at it. And tho' indeed we can neither perform the preparatory Duties to,
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:94102:14"/>nor the actual Duties in this Ordinance as we could wiſh; yet we are to labour after the attainment and performance thereof as well as we can, and be ſorry for our failures therein, and if we do ſo, upon the benefit of the Sacraments, we need not diſtruſt God's acceptance of us, as worthy thro' the Righteouſneſs of Chriſt.</p>
            <p>But on the other hand, if we do not come to the Sacrament in this ſenſe, if we have no Knowledge of what we do, and why we come to the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; if we have no hungrings and thirſtings af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter Chriſt, nor deſires to this Ordinance; if we come without Repentance or ſincere Reſolutions of Amendment, and are without Love to God, or without Charity and readineſs to forgive Men, when we at the ſame time do ſtand in need of, and beg God's forgiveneſs; if we do not believe in Chriſt, and are not thankful for what we Comme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morate and receive, we come unworthily, and to no purpoſe.</p>
            <p>It is the want of theſe preparatory and Orna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mental Graces that makes us unworthy; but as for Receiving the Sacrament with others that are unworthy, or for receiving it Kneeling, it makes us not unworthy Gueſts at the Lord's Table, which brings me to the latter part of the ſecond Head, <hi>viz.</hi> Upon what Account, and by what Ways Men do not receive the Sacrament of the Lords Supper unworthily.</p>
            <p>Now amongſt theſe I ſhall only in this Diſcourſe inſiſt upon two, and that the more largely, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they have been made by too many, the hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drances to the worthy receiving of the Lord's Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per, tho' in themſelves no ways the Cauſe of an unworthy Receiving: And they are theſe, 1. The Receiving of it with unworthy Perſons in a mixt
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:94102:15"/>Communion. 2. The Receiving of it in a Kneel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing poſture.</p>
            <p>As to the firſt, The Receiving of the Sacrament with unworthy Perſons in a mixt Communion, it is indeed much urg'd by ſome as a hindrance to a worthy receiving, but upon what reaſon I ſee not. If indeed my receiving of the Sacrament worthily depended upon others behaviour or unworthineſs, then it concern'd me to take Care that I did not communicate with any that were unworthy; but now the terms of a worthy receiving are not ſo uncertain, but rather ſuch as a private Communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cant is to look after as to himſelf; but <hi>let a Man examine himſelf, and ſo let him eat,</hi> 1 Cor. 11.28. As for others Examination of themſelves, or their worthineſs, they are to look to it upon their pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ril: And tho' a private Chriſtian as well as the Church ought to admoniſh profane and careleſs Perſons how they come, yet if notwithſtanding his Admonition, nay, what is further, the Churches, they will venture to come, it doth not make him that is a worthy Communicant otherwiſe, hereby to become an unworthy Communicant: For indeed ſhould this be ſo, not only the Apoſtles would have been unworthy Partakers of the Paſſeover and Sacrament, (becauſe a <hi>Judas</hi> was with them) but it may be moſt good Chriſtians beſides, that receive it in a publick Congregation, it being hard to ſay of the Members of any Congregation, that they are all ſo good, that there is no unworthy Member amongſt them.</p>
            <p>And now is this reaſonable, that good Mend worthy performance of this Duty ſhould become Evil, becauſe they receive with the unworthy, when yet that they were unworthy, is not the Good Mens fault? It is indeed my Duty to fit my ſelf as well as I can, and behave my ſelf reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rently
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:94102:15"/>at it, but if another will come unprepar'd, be it to himſelf, thô I deny not but I ought to be griev'd at the danger he runs himſelf into, and the ſcandal that he gives to others, yet as to the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefit of the Ordinance, his fault doth not make void God's Ordinance to me. And accordingly, tho' I can't ſay but we have many times unworthy Communicants amongſt us; yet many Good Men in receiving of the Sacrament amongſt us find be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefit thereby to their Souls, tho' it may be at the ſame time they are ſenſible, that ſome that receive with them have not given ſuch Evidences of their Repentance as might be wiſh'd.</p>
            <p>Nor indeed are they the more unworthy for re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiving it with them, becauſe they do not there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by joyn with them in their Sins, but in this part of God's Worſhip, which being a publick Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance for the Church, all the Communion of the Worthy with the unworthy is only a joyning to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether in the performance of a Common Duty to which good People are oblig'd to come, and that worthily, tho' others do not, which if they do not, it is their fault, and not Good mens.</p>
            <p>And ſad indeed would it be, That after all our Care and Endeavours to adorn our ſelves to this Marriage-Feaſt, we ſhould be forced to withdraw from it becauſe there ſhould come in one that had not on the Wedding Garment; but ſurely if he comes without it, it is his Fault, which tho' it renders him without excuſe, it doth not there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore make it no Feaſt to others, nor is it an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſe to any to ſtay away upon his account, and thereby to neglect their Duty.</p>
            <p>It's true indeed, that the Church ſhould purge out the leven from amongſt them, (1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.13.) and put away from it notorious Offenders; and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordingly not only St. <hi>Paul,</hi> but our Church in
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:94102:16"/>her Rubrick before the Communion advertiſeth, <q>That the Curate ſhall not ſuffer Perſons to come to the Lord's Table, in whom he perceiveth Malice or Hatred to reign, untill he know them to be reconciled; and that he is alſo to advertiſe, That none preſume to come to the Lord's Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble that are open ill Livers,</q> whilſt they are ſo; Yet if after all, either the Miniſter or the Church cannot for many Reaſons keep up its Diſcipline, or what is worſe to be ſuppos'd, do neglect it, yet this is not a making Worthy Communicants to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive unworthily, the Sacrament ſtill is a means of Grace to the Worthy partaker; ſo that as a famous Nonconformiſt declares, <hi>That tho' Wicked and Prophane Perſons pollute this Ordinance to them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, yet not to others, but he that believeth, eateth of the Bread of Life,</hi> John 6.33. which ſhall be made good to the Believer, tho' there were but one in the World: See <hi>Huſſey</hi>'s <hi>Plea for Chriſtian Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtracy,</hi> p. 2. And this he tells us <hi>Beza</hi> himſelf is in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forced to confeſs in his Tract againſt <hi>Eraſtus; Bonis manere bona Sacramenta etiamſi qui mali ad eadem ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cedunt, abſit ut inficiemur:</hi> The Sacraments remain effectual to the Good, tho' Evil Men come to them, far be it from us to deny it; ſo that the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment (ſaith he) remaineth holy to the Believers, and they are pure notwithſtanding the unprepared<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of the Wicked.</p>
            <p>And if it be not in the Power of the Miniſters of the Sacraments to hinder the good Effect of Chriſt's Ordinance, or to diminiſh the Grace of God's Gifts from ſuch as by Faith and rightly do receive them, which are effectual becauſe of Chriſt's Inſtitution and Promiſe, although they be mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtred by evil Men, as our Church declares in her <hi>26th.</hi> Article: Much leſs is it in the Power of Fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low Communicants, who are no more concern'd
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:94102:16"/>with our receiving it, than as they joyn with us in the outward performance of a common Duty.</p>
            <p>And that we may be the more ſatisfi'd in this thing, let us but take the Inſtance of <hi>Judas,</hi> and we ſhall find it very hard to conclude, that the other eleven Apoſtles were unworthy Receivers, or that Chriſt ought not to have eaten the Paſſeover with, or given the Sacrament to them, becauſe <hi>Judas</hi> was with them: For however ſome Perſons would ſeem to deny it, yet as it is plain that he was at the Paſſeover, ſo at the receiving of the Lord's Supper, which will appear ſo, if we con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider what the Evangeliſts ſay hereof. Thus in the <hi>22d. Luke</hi> we ſhall find it not only declar'd, that when the Paſſeover was ready, and the hour for it was come, <hi>he ſat down, and the twelve Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles with him,</hi> V. 14. but in the 19, 20, 21 Verſes we are told, That <hi>he took Bread, and gave thanks, and brake it amongſt them, and gave unto them, ſaying, This is my Body which is given for you: Do this in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membrance of me. And likewiſe alſo the Cup after Supper, ſaying, This Cup is the New Teſtament in my Blood, which is ſhed for you:</hi> And then follows, <hi>But behold the hand of him that betrayeth me, is with me on the Table.</hi> Now if <hi>Judas</hi> was the Perſon that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tray'd Chriſt, which is not deny'd, it follows, that it was his hand that was with him on the Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble; and if ſo, that then he was with Chriſt.</p>
            <p>So likewiſe if we look into the <hi>26th.</hi> of St. <hi>Matthew</hi>'s Goſpel, we find, that when <hi>Even was come, he ſat down with the twelve: And as they did eat, he ſaith, Verily one of you ſhall betray me,</hi> v. 20, 21. And when <hi>Judas</hi> ask'd whether it was he that ſhould do ſo, he not only gives a ſign who it ſhould be, but anſwers <hi>Judas</hi> it was he; <hi>Thou ſayſt it,</hi> V. 23.25. and in the <hi>26th.</hi> Verſe, follows the Inſtitution of the Sacrament of the Lord's Supper.
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:94102:17"/>
               <hi>And as they were eating, Jeſus took Bread,</hi> &amp;c. and in the <hi>27th.</hi> Verſe, <hi>He took the Cup and gave thanks, and gave it to them, ſaying, Drink ye all of it, for this is my Blood,</hi> &amp;c. V. <hi>28th.</hi> The like I might ſhew from the Account given thereof by St. <hi>Mark,</hi> Ch. 14. from V. 17. to V. 25. That where Chriſt ſpeaks of the Paſſeover or Lord's Supper to his Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples, it is not ſeparately to the other eleven, but to the twelve.</p>
            <p>Thus we ſee, that a <hi>Judas</hi> being amongſt Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municants, did not hinder Chriſt from inſtituting, nor his Diſciples from receiving the Lord's Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per, much leſs make them unworthy Communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cants.</p>
            <p>And tho' ſome, perhaps, may here aſſert, That <hi>Judas</hi>'s Unworthineſs was unknown, and that the Diſciples did not know that he was the Perſon that ſhould betray Chriſt, as appears by their que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion to Chriſt; <hi>Is it I? Is it I?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Yet I Anſwer, That ſuppoſing it was unknown to the Diſciples till Chriſt told them, yet they muſt allow, that Chriſt knew very well before<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hand who it was that was to betray him, and that <hi>Judas</hi> was the Perſon; and yet notwithſtanding he was known to be ſo by Chriſt, yet this did not hinder Chriſt from Inſtituting it, nor did it hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the other Apoſtles from being Worthy Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municants, tho' it is very probable that before thev receiv'd the Sacrament, they knew or were ſatisfied, that <hi>Judas</hi> was the Perſon that was to betray Chriſt,<note place="margin">Mar. 26. <hi>v.</hi> 23.</note> that ſign which Chriſt gave them, that he who <hi>dipt his hand with him in the Diſh, the ſame ſhould betray him;</hi> (Now the dipping of the hand in the Diſh was at the Eating of the Paſſeover, which was celebrated before the Lord's Supper, or the Inſtitution of the Sacrament,) and therefore they might have avoided him thereat;
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:94102:17"/>but we don't find that they had any ſuch demurrs, but they might as well receive it with <hi>Judas,</hi> as Chriſt give it to him, and yet be Worthy Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municants.</p>
            <p>Nay, let us come to the <hi>11th.</hi> Chapter of the firſt Epiſtle to the <hi>Corinthians,</hi> wherein we have the account of the danger of unworthy Receiving, and we ſhall not yet find that others unworthineſs made the Good to become unworthy, tho' ſome of them were ſo unworthy as to be drunk at the Receiving of the Lords Supper, and ſo did eat and drink unworthily; yet we don't read that St, <hi>Paul</hi> declares, that others that were not ſo as they, were therefore unworthy, but rather de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clares, <hi>Let a Man examine himſelf, and ſo let him <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>at,</hi> yea for the future they were not to ſeparate upon paſt faults, but to amend when they came together.</p>
            <p>Its true indeed from St. <hi>Paul</hi>'s words, it is law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful to cenſure Offenders, and ſeparate them from our Communion till they reform, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5 <hi>ch.</hi> from V. 7. to the end; yea with a Brother that is a For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicator, or ſuch like, with ſuch an one we are not to eat: By which words, as we are not to hold in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>timacy or Familiarity with ſcandalous Offenders, further than is neceſſary and convenient, we are <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ot to countenance them by our Friendſhip in their <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>vil Ways; ſo even the Church is to take Care to inhibit them a Spiritual Communion with us, (till they repent, or make Declarations thereof) and thereby to prevent their being offenſive to o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers at this Holy Ordinance.</p>
            <p>Yet if after the Churches Admonitions, or what is more, it's Neglects, wicked Men do venture up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on this Ordinance, and come to this Feaſt, not having on the Wedding Garment, this doth not make Good Men the more unworthy, it being un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reaſonable
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:94102:18"/>to think, that <hi>Judas</hi> his being with the other Diſeiples made them alſo unworthy; or that becauſe an ill Man ruſhes upon this Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance, therefore a Good Man ſhould go or ſtay away becauſe of him, or elſe he muſt receive amiſs, or that anothers Sin ſhould make me omit my Du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, or turn it into Sin.</p>
            <p>And as the Receiving of the Sacrament with Unworthy Perſons in a mixt Communion doth not make Men receive unworthily, where the Receiv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing with them is not a complying with them in their ſins, but a doing of our own Duty, and that upon the Command of Chriſt; ſo neither in the next place doth the receiving of the Sacrament in a Kneeling poſture. Great indeed have been the Clamours of ſome People againſt this Poſture, yea ſo unworthy hath it made Men (according to their Exclamations) that it renders them guilty of Idolatry, and makes them little leſs obnoxious to reproof than the Papiſts are for the Adoration of the Hoſt.</p>
            <p>But yet after all, the ſtrength of their Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>menss conſiſts moſt in popular Noiſe. And as our Church hath ſufficiently clear'd her ſelf from the Charge of Idolatry, and the countenancing of Tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſubſtantiation, ſo have its Members as ſufficiently prov'd the Innocence of this poſture of Kneel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling.</p>
            <p>And tho' indeed there needs little to be added to what they have written already, it being ſo clear and full, particularly in the Treatiſe, call'd <hi>The Caſe of Kneeling at the Sacrament,</hi> 1ſt. and 2d. Part: Yet it ſtill continuing an Objection in the mouths of ſome againſt holding Communion with our Church, I beg leave to conſider their Reaſons why the Kneelling at the Sacrament makes Men
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:94102:18"/>to receive it unworthily, amongſt which I look upon theſe to be the chief.</p>
            <p n="1">1. That Kneeling is not the poſture in which Chriſt gave, and his Apoſtles receiv'd it.</p>
            <p n="2">2. That Kneeling being a Poſture of Worſhip and Adoration, it too much countenanceth the Adoration of the Hoſt, and the Doctrine of Tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſubſtantiation.</p>
            <p>Now if theſe Objections will not hold good, then it will not appear from them, that Kneeling at the Sacrament makes Men to receive it unwor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thily.</p>
            <p>To conſider therefore their firſt Reaſon againſt Kneeling at the Sacrament, <hi>viz.</hi> That Kneeling is not the Poſture in which Chriſt and his Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles receiv'd it. To which I Anſwer: 1. That this is more than can be proved. 2. That if Kneeling was not the Poſture in which Chriſt gave, and his Apoſtles receiv'd it, yet it doth not fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low therefore that Kneeling is an unſuitable Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſture, or makes Men receive the Sacrament unwor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thily.</p>
            <p>As to the firſt, That this is more than can be prov'd, that Kneeling was not the Poſture in which they receiv'd it, appears from hence, That the Poſture in which they receiv'd it, is no where mentioned in Scripture. A plain Command we have to receive the Sacrament of the Lord's Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per in Scripture, but in what poſture, whether ſtanding, ſitting or kneeling, it is not determin'd by Chriſt and his Apoſtles; and therefore as they are all poſtures in themſelves lawful, ſo they are ſeverally uſed according to the different Conſtituti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of Churches; ſome taking it in one poſture, and ſome in another, the Geſture at it being but a mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of Circumſtance, and not expreſly Commanded, even in the Judgment of many Nonconformiſts.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="30" facs="tcp:94102:19"/>
As for what is urg'd, That it is probable, that Chriſt did give, and his Apoſtles did take the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament in the ſame Poſture as they did the Paſſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>over, and that was as they ſate, it will not at all appear to be a proof: For tho' it be ſaid, That <hi>as they were eating, Jeſus took Bread, and bleſſed it,</hi> &amp;c. Mat. 26.26. and that the Cuſtom of the Jews was in Chriſt's time to eat in a lying or leaning poſture, (which was with them a Table poſture, as ſitting is with us;) and therefore in the <hi>26th. Mat. v.</hi> 20. where it is ſaid, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, we render it, <hi>when the Evening was come, he ſat down with the twelve;</hi> yet this is not becauſe the word primarily ſigniſies to ſit, ſo that the Apoſtles ſate as we do, but becauſe that this being a Table poſture with them, we expreſs the word by ours.</p>
            <p>But Secondly, Suppoſe that they did ſit down ſometimes at the Paſſeover, as we do at our meals, yet it doth not appear by any Text that they re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mained in the ſame Poſture; nay Learned Men tell us, [See <hi>Lightfoot</hi>'s <hi>Hora Hebraei,</hi> in <hi>26th.</hi> Mat. v. 20. <hi>Caſe of Kneeling,</hi> 1 part. <hi>p.</hi> 19.22.] That it is amongſt the Jewiſh Records, that Perſons did not always keep the ſame poſture in eating the Paſſeover, but when they came to ſome particular Cups, and the Diſh of bitter Herbs, they forbore the inclining or leaning poſture: However, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the Jews did keep always the ſame Poſture or not at the Paſſeover, it doth not appear by Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture that Chriſt and his Apoſtles kept in the ſame Poſture at the Sacrament as at the Paſſeover, on that they did keep the ſame poſture all the time of the Celebration of the Paſſeover; it might be ſo, or it might not be ſo, for any thing that we read to the contrary, and therefore the Noncon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formiſts do not ſo far aſſert the neceſſity of ſitting
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:94102:19"/>from our Saviours behaviour, but allow the ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king of the Sacrament ſtanding.</p>
            <p>And ſo I proceed to the next thing which I pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pos'd to prove in anſwer to the firſt Reaſon, which is this: That if Kneeling was not the poſture in which Chriſt gave, and the Apoſtles receiv'd the Sacrament, yet it doth not follow therefore, that Kneeling is an unſuitable poſture, or makes Men to receive the Sacrament unworthily. And that firſt, Becauſe all that Chriſt did is not bind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to us, but where it is declar'd as binding, or is an illuſtration of ſome Rule, and conſequently all the Geſtures and Circumſtances in our Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ours actings are not a Rule for ours; for if they were, then in the Receiving of the Sacrament, we muſt take it leaning or lying down, as the poſture of eating amongſt the Jews then was, we muſt receive it in an upper Room, and with Men only, and that only after Supper, and the like.</p>
            <p>But this is ſo abſurd to maintain, that our Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenting Brethren do own that it is not Obligato<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, and that Geſture is not of the Freehold of this Ordinance. [See Mr. <hi>Vines</hi> on the Sacrament, and Mr. <hi>Baxter</hi> in his <hi>Chriſtian Directory,</hi> part. 2. Queſt. 3. Sect. 40. Chap. 24. p. 60.] Nay Chriſt's own Example (ſuppoſing that he gave, and his Diſciples receiv'd of him the Sacrament in the ſame poſture as he did the Paſſeover) makes ſtrongly for Kneeling, becauſe in taking the Paſſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>over according to the Cuſtom of the Jews, (which was ſitting ſay our Brethren, but was leaning or lying along, ſay the words in the Original, and the Cuſtom of the Countrey.) And in complying with the Geſture of the Jews then in uſe, he al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low'd thereby the Authority of the Church in al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tering and determining of Geſtures: For it is plain, that however the Geſture at the Paſſeover
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:94102:20"/>was ſitting or leaning, yet this was not the po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſture at firſt us'd and preſcrib'd by <hi>Moſes, Exod.</hi> 2. <hi>ch.</hi> The Geſture that was at firſt appointed, was with their Loyns girt, with their Shooes on their Feet in haſte, with a Staff in their hands, which way of eating it being but a Temporary Law, after they were in <hi>Canaan,</hi> they kept it in the leaning poſture, thereby to ſhew, that now they were free from the fears of <hi>Egypt,</hi> and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore did not eat it in haſte, but in a poſture of Reſt and Security: And now if Chriſt comply'd with the alteration of the poſture to what it was at firſt, it ſhews, that in matters of Geſture unde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termin'd by God, we ought to ſubmit to the Cuſtoms and Uſage of the Church wherein we live.</p>
            <p>Nor doth it make Men the more unworthy Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceivers of the Sacrament, that they Kneel at the Receiving of it, becauſe as ſome ſay, the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment is a Feaſt, and is call'd the Lord's Supper, and therefore ought to be receiv'd in a Table Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſture, which to be ſure is not Kneeling; for tho' it be a Feaſt (as it is indeed for the Souls of Men) it doth not therefore follow, that all things are to be done at it in a Feaſt way, for if ſo, then we may talk and laugh, or the like: But ſurely upon Conſideration Men will be more wiſe than to aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſert, That becauſe the Sacrament is call'd a Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per, or Feaſt, therefore the Circumſtances of a Natural Feaſt, or Supper, are appropriate unto it.</p>
            <p>And therefore ſome of our Brethren urge a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt this Argument themſelves, (<hi>viz.</hi> That we muſt fit, becauſe ſitting is a Table Geſture at a Supper, or Feaſt, and is a Token of our Freedom and Fellowſhip with Chriſt,) That upon the ſame Reaſon (ſay they) we may as well put on our
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:94102:20"/>Hats when we receive the Sacrament. See <hi>Refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med Diſſenter,</hi> p. 6.</p>
            <p>Nor indeed is Kneeling an unſuitable poſture at the Sacrament, if we conſider, That when we re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive the Sacrament of the Lord's Supper, we re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive it with a Prayer; nay, in Receiving of it we by ſenſible Signs do the Duties and Parts of Prayer; in receiving of it for the Remiſſion of Sins, we thereby confeſs our ſelves Sinners, yea we implore the pardon of them upon the Merits of Chriſt's Sufferings: As alſo in receiving of Chriſt we do hereby ſhew, that we beg Grace and Aſſiſtance of God, it being of his fulneſs that we receive Grace for Grace, <hi>John</hi> 1.16. The like I might ſhew in other parts of Prayer as we uſe them, <hi>viz.</hi> Interceſſion and Thankſgiving — yea further than this, that the receiving of the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment contains a Virtual praying to, and giving Thanks to God. We that are Members of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> receive it with a Prayer, <hi>viz. The Body of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt which was given for thee, preſerve thy Body and Soul unto Everlaſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Life:</hi> And then follows, <hi>Take, eat,</hi> &amp;c. The like I might ſhew is done at the giving of the Cup.</p>
            <p>And now if this be ſo, which is not to be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny'd, it follows, that Kneeling is not unſuitable to the Nature and Actions of this Ordinance, it being a fit and proper poſture of Praiſe and Thankſgiving.</p>
            <p>And if any Man thinks otherwiſe, let him but conſider the practice of Heathens, yea of Diſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters in their Domeſtick Devotions; but if theſe will not bear weight with him, let him conſider the practice of Chriſt, St. <hi>Paul,</hi> St. <hi>Stephen,</hi> and he'll find plain Inſtances of Kneeling in Prayer: yea do we but conſider our Saviour in his Ago<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:94102:21"/>which we Commemorate at the Sacrament, and we ſhall find that even then he did not reck<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on it unbecoming him to kneel at his Devotion, <hi>Luke</hi> 22.41.</p>
            <p>And now ſince that the principal parts of the Sacramental Actions on our part are Prayer, Praiſe, and the like, and that either verbally or virtually; and that Kneeling is agreeable to theſe great and Spiritual parts of it, it is ſo far from being unſuitable, that it is highly becoming this Ordinance, not only as it is a poſture agreeable with the Nature and Uſe of Prayer and Praiſe, but as a poſture of Worſhip to Chriſt, and as our Church expreſſeth it, A ſignification of an humble and grateful Acknowledgment of the Benefits of Chriſt therein given to all Worthy Receivers; which brings me to the Conſideration of the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond Reaſon, that ſome Men urge why the Kneel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing at the Sacrament makes Men to receive it un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthily, <hi>viz.</hi> That Kneeling being a poſture of Worſhip and Adoration, it too much countenan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceth the Adoration of the Hoſt, and the Doctrine of Tranſubſtantiation. That we uſe Kneeling as a poſture of Worſhip, is what we allow; but that thereby we countenance the Adoration of the Hoſt, or the Doctrine of Tranſubſtantiation, is a thing unreaſonably laid to our Charge, conſidering not only what our Church declares in her Rubrick af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the Communion Service, but with what ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lidity and ſtrength of Argument they have Confu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted the Abettors of ſuch Doctrines as they are, and in a time when others that have exclaim'd a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt our Church for bending towards Popery, either durſt not, or would not write againſt it.</p>
            <p>Nor indeed are we to be blam'd for worſhip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping at this Ordinance, when by Faith we ſee Chriſt preſent with us, yea in as much as we pray
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:94102:21"/>to and praiſe Chriſt, and celebrate his Goodneſs, we do therein Worſhip, (Prayer and Thankſgiv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing being actions of Worſhip) and that by the Confeſſions of our Diſſenting Brethren, who al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low that Chriſt may be Worſhip'd and Ador'd by Communicants in their Hearts. And now ſince In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternal Worſhip belongs to Chriſt in this Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance, why may not we uſe an External ſign of what we inwardly proseſs to do? Nay, it upon the ſenſe of what we do and receive at the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, we may lift up our eyes and hands towards Heaven, and ſmite our Breaſts, why may not we as well kneel at our Worſhip too? It being a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venient Geſture, ſuch as was practis'd by Chriſt, and is even now by many good Men in their Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip. Surely Geſture is as lawful in one Circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance as in another, and I may as well bow my Knees to the Father of the Lord Jeſus, as bow my Head, or lift up my Eyes, a humble poſture of Body being not unſuitable to an humble Mind.</p>
            <p>Nor indeed doth kneeling at the Sacrament countenance the Adoration of the Hoſt, or the Doctrine of Tranſubſtantiation, becauſe tho' we Worſhip at the Sacrament in this poſture, yet we do not Worſhip the Sacrament, or make it the Object of our Worſhip, (as the Papiſts do) any more than the Diſſenters themſelves, when they pray to, and praiſe God at the receiving of the Sacrament: For if by expreſſing our inward Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip by this poſture of outward Worſhip, we are therefore Adorers of the Hoſt, it will follow that they too are guilty of the like Crime, for to Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip inwardly is Worſhipping, as well as uſing an outward Geſture of Worſhip.</p>
            <p>But as we do not Charge our Diſſenting Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren with this fault, ſo neither are we to be charg'd therewith, it being not the Elements that
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:94102:22"/>are the Object of our inward or outward Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, but that which is ſignify'd thereby; and it being our Duty in this Ordinance to be inwardly devout, humble and thankful, they are not there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore to find fault with Kneeling, which is but an outward Declaration of our inward Reſpect.</p>
            <p>It's true indeed, that the Sacraments are Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinances of Remembrance, the very End of their Inſtitution is to do them in remembrance of Chriſt, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.25. but becauſe they are ſo, we are not therefore forbid to kneel at them more than at Prayer, which brings God into our remembrance: And tho' I deny not that we Worſhip before the Elements, yet this is no more Argument that we Worſhip them, than that the Children of <hi>Iſrael</hi> could be ſaid to Worſhip the Ark or the Temple when they fell down in or before it. And we may as well ſay, that the <hi>Jews</hi> when they cry'd <hi>Hoſanna</hi> to Chriſt riding upon an Aſs, worſhip'd the Aſs, as ſay that every Circumſtance in Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip is the Object of it.</p>
            <p>Nor is the Geſture of Kneeling the leſs unſuit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able to this Ordinance, nor do we the more en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courage the Adoration of the Hoſt, tho' we uſe kneeling, allowing that the ſame Geſture is us'd by the Papiſts in their Adoration of the Hoſt; for if ſo, we may as well be ſaid to countenance them in their Worſhipping of Saints, becauſe we kneel at our Prayers to God as well as they do at their Prayers to Saints: What tho' the Papiſts kneel, muſt not we therefore? What tho' they ſay the Lord's Prayer, may not we? It is not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the Papiſts do ſuch and ſuch things that is a good Reaſon for our not doing them, becauſe they do ill therein. Many People we ſee abuſe themſelves by Intemperate Eating or Drinking, but will it follow, therefore that we may not eat
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:94102:22"/>or drink? And ſo the Papiſts, we deny not, are guilty of Idolatry and Superſtition in the matter of the Sacrament as well as other things, muſt we therefore? By this Reaſon the <hi>Jews</hi> ſhould not have ſacrific'd or burnt Incenſe, becauſe the Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thens uſed the ſame Rites: Nay, by this Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, that the Papiſts kneeling at the Sacrament, and doing ill thereby, ſhould make our kneeling at it to be ſinful, we ſhould be in a continual dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger of loſing that Liberty wherewith Chriſt hath made us free, the ſame being an Argument againſt ſitting or ſtanding, as well as kneeling at the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament, ſhou'd they either ſtand or ſit at it.</p>
            <p>And indeed, however we are accus'd of favour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Popery, as upon other accounts, ſo for kneel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing at the Sacrament, yet we don't find kneeling at the receiving of the Sacrament ſo much a tenet of the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> as that none other is al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low'd amongſt them; for if you believe their <hi>Miſſal</hi> ſet out by Pope <hi>Pius</hi> the <hi>5th,</hi> we are told, that the Prieſt, tho' at the Elevation of the Hoſt, he is to kneel, yet at the Receiving of it is to ſtand, and accordingly it was ſo practis'd by the Popiſh Prieſts not long ſince in this Kingdom: Nay, as Learned Men have ſhewn, <q>The Pope himſelf not only us'd to ſit at the receiving of the Sacrament, as in <hi>Bonaventure</hi>'s time, but even now ordinari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly he receives it leaning, and extraordinarily, or when he celebrates Maſs himſelf, ſtanding:</q> See <hi>Stillingfleet</hi>'s <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nreaſon. Separation,</hi> p. 15. <hi>Caſe of Kneeling,</hi> pt. 2. pag. 38, 39. By which we ſee, that notwithſtanding the Clamours of ſome Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, the poſture of Kneeling at the Sacrament is not ſo unſuitable to the Ordinance of the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, it being a poſture that may be us'd with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any Countenancing of the Adoration of the Hoſt, or the Doctrine of Tranſubſtantiation; the
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:94102:23"/>Abettors of which poſitions are ſuch as allow of other poſtures beſides kneeling, which are not therefore diſallow'd by Diſſenters becauſe uſed by Papiſts, nor are they uſed by us as a countenan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing of them: And now if kneeling amongſt us be not uſed any ways to countenance the aforeſaid Errors of the Papiſts, but is declar'd by the Church not to be ſo deſign'd or uſed, it can't make us guilty of unworthy Receiving.</p>
            <p>And thus have I given an Anſwer to the chief Objections againſt Kneeling at the Sacrament; which Anſwer, tho' ſupported with a borrow'd ſtrength from the Writings of ſeveral upon this Subject, as well as from its own force, yet is not therefore the leſs convincing, but may be of good uſe to prove, that by our kneeling at the Lord's Supper, if we have no other failures, we do not eat and drink unworthily, nor are we unworthy Communicants.</p>
            <p>And thus have I at large ſhewn, Upon what Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count, and by what Ways Men receive the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the Lord's Supper unworthily, or are un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthy Communicants, and upon what they do not.</p>
            <p>I come now in the next place to ſhew in what ſenſe the receiving of it unworthily is ſo dange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous as it is ſaid to be in the Text, which was the third thing that I propos'd to treat of from the words of the Text.</p>
            <p>Now the words of the Text are: <hi>For he that eateth and drinketh unworthily, eateth and drinketh Dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation to himſelf. Damnation,</hi> a very terrible word, but much more terrible thing, as it is taken for Eternal Damnation, and could not be taken in another ſenſe: But yet both in the Notion of it and the Application of it by St. <hi>Paul,</hi> it admits of
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:94102:23"/>another acceptation. The word in the Original is <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> which coming from <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, to judge or diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cern, ſignifies Judgment, diſcerning, or cenſuring, and accordingly in the Margents of many Bibles, it is put <hi>Judgment,</hi> by which is not only meant Eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal, but Temporal Judgment alſo; and that it may be ſo taken will appear the more, in that we find the word actively applyed unto Men.</p>
            <p>Thus in the <hi>7th. Mat.</hi> v. 2. it is ſaid of Men, <hi>With what judgment ye judge, ſhall ye be judged.</hi> The words in the Original are <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Now it is it plain, that in this place it relates on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to Temporal cenſuring, or Judgment, becauſe it is not in the power of Men to inflict Eternal Judgment.</p>
            <p>And as the word in the Original doth not car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry with it univerſally ſuch a dreadful ſignificati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on as Eternal Damnation: So neither is it taken by St. <hi>Paul</hi> in this ſenſe, for if we conſider what follows theſe words of the Text, we ſhall find it primarily or chiefly relating to Temporal Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, for after he had ſhewn in this Chapter how the <hi>Corinthians</hi> had eaten unworthily the Lord's Supper, <hi>v.</hi> 20, 21. in the <hi>27th.</hi> and <hi>29th.</hi> Verſes he ſhews them the danger of their actions, and that they may not think the danger of their Actions to conſiſt only in words, in the <hi>30th.</hi> Verſe he proves it to them from their own Experience; <hi>That for this Cauſe</hi> (to wit, their unworthy eating and drinking, or receiving of the Lord's Supper) <hi>ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny were weak and ſickly amongſt them, and many were aſleep:</hi> He particularizes in the Judgments they had brought upon themſelves thereby.</p>
            <p>Now that theſe Judgments were not Eternal, not only the Inſtances thereof, but the words fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing do plainly declare, <hi>That if they judg'd themſelves, they ſhould not be judged;</hi> if they would
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:94102:24"/>cenſure this fault in themſelves, they ſhould not any more be ſo judged as they were in the <hi>30th.</hi> Verſe.</p>
            <p>But when by not judging of our ſelves we put God upon judging, or in the Apoſtles words are judged, why then it follows, that <hi>we are chaſtned of the Lord,</hi> v. 32. How? not for ever, but that we ſhou'd not be condemn'd with the World: By which it appears, that the Judgments of God are ſo far from ſignifying Eternal, or everlaſting dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation, that he propoſeth it as an end of theſe Judgments to avoid being judg'd or condemn'd with the World.</p>
            <p>Nay, ſo far is the word <hi>Damnation</hi> in the Text from being to be taken as ſignifying primarily, Eternal, that till Men are impenitent in their un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthy Receiving, we find St. <hi>Paul</hi> to be ſo far from conſigning the <hi>Corinthians</hi> (tho' Unworthy Recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers) to Eternal Damnation, that he rather ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>horts them, and that as Brethren, that when they met hereafter, they ſhould amend this Fault: <hi>Wherefore my Brethren, when ye come together to eat, tarry one for another; and if any man hunger, let him eat at home, that ye come not together unto Condemnati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,</hi> v. 33, 34.</p>
            <p>Its true, That if a Man by his unworthy receiv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the Lord's Supper hath brought Temporal Judgments upon himſelf, and is not thereby wrought to Repentance; or if he perſiſts habitually in un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthy approaches to, or behaviour at this Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinance, he doth not only bring himſelf in danger of greater Temporal Judgments, but Eternal alſo: And ſo indeed not only any Perſon that receives the Lords Supper unworthily, but he that prays, reads or hears unworthily, doth ſo too.</p>
            <p>In ſhort, the Damnation that a Man incurrs in this Caſe, is but as that which he brings upon
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:94102:24"/>himſelf by other Sins, for which every Man ſhall be damn'd, unleſs he Repent, or ſincerely deſires and endeavours ſo to do; but if he doth Repent of this as well as other Sins, he is not in a ſtate of Damnation, tho' he hath formerly receiv'd un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthily — And tho Damnation may be the por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of an unworthy Receiver not repenting, yet it may be alſo the portion of him that lives in a To<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal and Wilful Neglect of this Ordinance, as well as of him that receives it unworthily; which brings me to the next Head I propos'd to treat of from the words of the Text, which was this:</p>
            <p>
               <hi>4th. Head.</hi> That tho' it be very dangerous to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive the Sacrament of the Lord's Supper unwor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thily, yet the Total and Wilful Neglect thereof is as dangerous: And that the not partaking of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Ordinances worthily, makes men lyable to Damnation as well as the not partaking of this Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament worthily: And that becauſe it is as ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary a Duty to come to the Sacrament, as it is not to come unworthily to it, to which tho' we can't come as we ſhould, we are yet to come as we can, as I ſhall ſhew in the cloſe of this Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe.</p>
            <p>For however there may be greater Excuſe and Allowance to a Man that ſtays away for fear, than there is to a Man that comes unworthily to the Sacrament, at the firſt Apprehenſion; yet if the Man that ſtays away out of fear doth not uſe his beſt Endeavours to remove that fear, and fit himſelf for it, he is as inexcuſeable as the other. For a Man to ſay, I will not receive the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment leſt I ſhould receive it unworthily, and yet not to ſtrive after preparation, or fitneſs in a Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel ſenſe, nor to inform himſelf when he is fit, is but little better than for a Man to ſay he will not be a Chriſtian, becauſe if he ſhould live ill, it
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:94102:25"/>would be worſe with him than if he had not been a Chriſtian: <hi>He that knoweth his Maſters Will, and will not do it, ſhall indeed be beaten with many ſtripes;</hi> but he that will not know it when he may, becauſe he would not fall into greater Condemnation, doth not therefore make his Caſe the better, but the worſe, in that he Evacuates to himſelf one means of avoiding Condemnation, <hi>viz.</hi> the Know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of that will which directs him to avoid it.</p>
            <p>The like is it with a Man that wilfully forbears the Sacrament, that ſo as he thinks he may eſcape the danger of unworthy Receiving, which tho' he avoids the danger of, yet he doth not avoid the danger of an Unworthy and <hi>wilful</hi> Neglect; which however men don't ſo much conſider of as they ought, is none of the leaſt, as I ſhall ſhew preſently: For let a Man be never ſo Cautious leſt he receive unworthily, if he makes not his fears an Argument for greater Care in his Prepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations and Endeavours to fit himſelf, his Fear, tho' it is not joyn'd with ſomething of Contempt, yet at beſt carries with it a great deal of Superſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, or undue Fear of God, and ſhews there is many times too much Careleſneſs of Spirit in Mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of ſo great Conſequence as the receiving of the Sacrament is.</p>
            <p>So that whatſoever allowable Excuſes there may be for our Abſence from it at ſome particular times, yet there are none for his <hi>Careleſneſs,</hi> who lives in a total and wilful Neglect thereof, where it may not only be had, but Inſtructions alſo as to the Rules and Neceſſity of Receiving it: And that becauſe as it is our Duty and Intereſt not to receive it unworthily; ſo is there a plain Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand for the Receiving it, which nothing can ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſe the <hi>total</hi> and <hi>wilful</hi> breach of.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="43" facs="tcp:94102:25"/>
But that we may not think this Aſſertion pure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly begg'd, <hi>viz.</hi> That the total and wilful Neglect of Receiving the Sacrament of the Lord's Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per, is as dangerous as the Receiving of it Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthily: I proceed to prove it in theſe follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Inſtances: 1. In regard of the unworthy deal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing with Chriſt. 2. With the Sacrament it ſelf.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Firſt,</hi> If we conſider the unworthy dealing with Chriſt, by a total and wilful Neglect of the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. And well indeed may we call it ſo, when by ſo doing we live in a total and wilful Neglect of his dying Command.</p>
            <p>Now that Chriſt hath Commanded us to receive the Sacrament, I think is ſo clear, that to que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion it, would be to queſtion the Inſtitution of our Saviour, of which we have ſo full an account in ſeveral of the Evangeliſts, and which is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firm'd to us by St. <hi>Paul</hi> in 11 Chapter of his firſt Epiſtle to the <hi>Corinthians.</hi> And now when we have ſo plain a Command, do not we deal very un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthily by him, when tho' we call him <hi>Lord, Lord, yet we do not the things he ſaith?</hi> Luke 6.46.</p>
            <p>But <hi>Secondly,</hi> Well may we ſay that a <hi>total</hi> and <hi>wilful</hi> Neglect of this Ordinance, is an unworthy dealing with Chriſt, if we conſider how ungrate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful dealing it is with him alſo. I ſuppoſe none pretend to be true Chriſtians, or pretend to ſtay away from this Ordinance out of fear that they ſhall not be fit for it, but what have ſome ſence of the Nature and Deſign of this Ordinance, that it is inſtituted as a Memorial of Chrſt's Suffer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings for us, and the Benefits thereof: And now how unworthily do we deal with him? Tho' we hope to be ſav'd by the Merits of his Sufferings, yet we wilfully neglect to celebrate the Memori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>als of them, or do ſo much in remembrance of him,
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:94102:26"/>as <hi>thankfully</hi> to ſhew forth his Death till he comes, in ways of his own appointment.</p>
            <p>But perhaps here ſome may ſay, <hi>That we can think of Chriſt's Love to Men in ſuffering for them, without coming to this Ordinance.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To which I Anſwer, I don't ſay but they may, but yet not ſo acceptably with God, ſo long as they live in the neglect of this appointed way of Remembrance; becauſe Chriſt hath appointed this as the great Memorial, and therefore may well take it ill when Men neglect his Way and Time of Remembrance, and ſtick only to their own, which if they could remember his Love as accepta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly in, as in that which he hath appointed, why did he appoint ſuch an Ordinance for this end? Certainly we ought not to think any thing impertinent, or of little uſe and acceptance which he hath Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded, much leſs that which indeed is the great Ordinance of conveying the pardon of Sin, and confirming our Intereſt in Chriſt.</p>
            <p>Surely if any Man under the Law ſhou'd plead for his Neglect of Sacrificing, tho' God com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded Sacrifices, that he could pray to God well enough, tho' he offer'd up no Sacrifice, ſuch an Excuſe or Plea would not have been allow'd, but would have been reckon'd as a Virtual deſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing of Sacrifices as unneceſſary, and conſequently wou'd have been very dangerous; for ſo it is ſaid, that <hi>he that despis'd Moſes his Law, dyed without mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy,</hi> Heb. 10.28.</p>
            <p>And now ſince Chriſt hath not only done ſo much for us, but hath left it in Charge at his Death, that we ſhould <hi>Take and Eat,</hi> yea that we ſhould <hi>all Drink</hi> in remembrance of him, and we look up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on this Charge as neceſſary to be obſerv'd by us; can we think he will not take it ill at our hands, and puniſh us for our Neglect, unleſs we repent?
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:94102:26"/>Yea ſaith the Apoſtle, <hi>See that ye refuſe not him that speaketh; for if they eſcaped not who refus'd him that ſpake on Earth, much more ſhall not we eſcape, if we turn away from him who ſpeaketh from Heaven,</hi> Heb. 12.25.</p>
            <p>But <hi>Secondly,</hi> It will appear, that a <hi>total</hi> and <hi>wilful</hi> Neglect of the Sacrament of the Lord's Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per, is as dangerous as the receiving it unwor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thily, in regard of the unworthy dealing there is thereby with the Sacrament it ſelf: For by a <hi>total</hi> and <hi>wilful</hi> Neglect of this Ordinance, we either ſhew that we do not reckon it a neceſſary Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance, which yet is the moſt ſolemn Ordinance in the Chriſtian Worſhip, (that is, a Memorial of his great Love, and a ſhewing forth of his Death till he comes:) Or elſe we make it (to uſe the word) a Bugbear, or more dreadful than it is, and ſo deal unworthily by it, when we act as if it was ſuch an Ordinance that was a greater oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion of Offence or Ruine than any other; in that we ſuppoſe it as one, that is leſs poſſible to be done worthily as to God's acceptance than any other; which to ſuppoſe, is not only to have un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gracious Thoughts of it, but is a reflecting upon the Goodneſs as well as Wiſdom of Chriſt, who hath order'd this as a means for our Salvation, if we are but ſincere, as indeed we ought, as well as <hi>pretend to be,</hi> in other Ordinances.</p>
            <p>I am apt to think, that many of theſe Men who ſtay away altogether from this Ordinance, for fear, as they ſay, leaſt if they come to it they ſhould come unworthily, are yet apt to hope, that (notwithſtanding their unfitneſs to receive the Sacrament) if they ſhould happen to dye, they ſhall receive the things ſignify'd by the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament, <hi>viz.</hi> The pardon of their Sins, and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conciliation
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:94102:27"/>with God thro' the Merits of Chriſts Sufferings.</p>
            <p>And now if theſe Perſons notwithſtanding their unworthineſs for the Receiving of the Sacrament, do yet truſt in God's Mercy for the receiving of the things ſignify'd and exhibited in the Sacrament, why may they not alſo truſt God's Mercy for the receiving of the ſign? If they truſt to receive the benefits of Chriſt's Merits, why ſhould they diſtruſt the Inſtitutions for that end: Nay, if any of theſe Perſons ſhould lie upon a Death-bed, upon asking. I ſuppoſe they would be ready to aſſert their hopes of Salvation through the Merits of Chriſt, tho they were unworthy of it: and now are not Men that are ſincere in what they ſay, as fit to receive the Sacrament as they are fit to Dye? Yea ſurely, if they are not fit to receive the Sacrament, they are not fit to dye, or receive the pardon of their Sins; for indeed I cannot find where God is ſaid to be more merciful to Men at their Death than at the Sacrament, it being very eaſily to be be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieved, that he who will pardon us when we come to dye, will pardon us alſo when we pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pare our ſelves as well as we can to receive the Sacrament; it being as eaſie alſo to think, that thoſe whom God will receive as fit for Heaven, he will receive alſo as fit for his Ordinances upon Earth: and therefore Perſons deal very unworthi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly with this, when they repreſent it as more dread<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful than it is.</p>
            <p>But <hi>Thirdly,</hi> It will appear, that a <hi>total</hi> and <hi>wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful</hi> Neglect of the Sacrament of the Lords Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per, is as dangerous as the Receiving it unwor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thily, if we conſider, that the being without thoſe preparatory and Ornamental Graces which ſhould make us receive worthily, doth as well expoſe
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:94102:27"/>us to the Danger of Damnation, when we do not receive the Sacrament, as when we do re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive it: If a Man hath the Qualifications of a Worthy Communicant, he is fit to receive; but if he hath them not, whether he receives the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament or no, he is in a miſerable eſtate.</p>
            <p>Thus for Inſtance, if a Man is without Repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, whether he comes to the Sacrament or not, he is like to periſh, <hi>Luke</hi> 13.3. or if he doth not believe, he is like to be damned, <hi>John</hi> 3.18. nay, he is condemned already; or if a Man knows not Chriſt, <hi>he hath no Eternal Life abiding in him,</hi> John 17.3. or if he is not in Charity, he is a Murderer, <hi>and no Murderer,</hi> St. <hi>John</hi> tells us, <hi>hath Eternal life abiding in him;</hi> 1 <hi>John</hi> 3.15. or <hi>if he forgives not men their Treſpaſſes, neither will his Heavenly Father for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>give his;</hi> Ch. 6. <hi>v.</hi> 15. yea he that hath no deſires after Chriſt, nor Love to him, can't be happy in Chriſt, nor by him; or if he is not thankful to God for his Love in Chriſt, he is unworthy of it, whether he receives the Sacrament or not.</p>
            <p>Nor is it an Argument that Men are the freer from Damnation, becauſe ſo long as they do not come to the Sacrament, they do not make a Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cramental Vow or Covenant to Live well; for tho' they never come to the Sacrament, they are yet oblig'd to live as well as they can; there is a Natural Obligation upon them to obey God in all his Commands, from which they are not diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charg'd, becauſe they do not receive the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment: For ſuppoſe Men never make any verbal or formal Covenant, it is not to be ſuppos'd that God loſeth the leaſt right to the utmoſt of their ſervice, or that he will the ſooner diſpenſe with them, becauſe they will not accept of another tye to ſerve him.</p>
            <pb n="46" facs="tcp:94102:28"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="47" facs="tcp:94102:28"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="48" facs="tcp:94102:29"/>
            <p>Its true indeed, that he who receives the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, doth thereby lay a further tye upon him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, and makes the bond double; but yet this doth not make Holineſs the leſs binding to one that doth not receive, the Natural Right that God hath to it being an indiſſoluble bond to man to practiſe it.</p>
            <p>Nay, he that will not receive the Sacrament becauſe he will not make an actual Engagement to Live better, is more inexcuſeable in ſome Reſpects than one that makes and breaks it; for he makes one ſin a reaſon for another, and ſhews an unwillingneſs to be oblig'd to God's Service ſo far as he may: But the other tho' he breaks his Tye, yet by ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing himſelf, declares that he owns it as his Duty to be ſo ty'd, and that he ought to live up to it: So that to neglect the Receiving of the Sacrament, and that wilfully too, to avoid the danger of un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthy Receiving, is but at beſt running into one danger to avoid another.</p>
            <p>But <hi>Fourthly,</hi> It will appear that a total and wilful Neglect of receiving the Sacrament of the Lords Supper, is as dangerous as the receiving it unworthily, becauſe thoſe things which make us unworthy Receivers are no Excuſe for a total and wilful Abſence from, or Neglect of the Lord's Supper.</p>
            <p>Now that which makes Men unworthy Receiv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, I told you, is not only Sin, but either want of Knowledge, or of Deſires to Chriſt; the want alſo of Charity, Repentance, Faith, Devotion, Thankfulneſs, and the like: The want then of theſe things being ſo ill as to make Men unwor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy Receivers, the Queſtion is, Whether the want of theſe is a juſt excuſe for a <hi>total</hi> and <hi>wilful</hi> Neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect of this Duty. Now the want of theſe being
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:94102:29"/>ſo ill, I anſwer, That it can't be an Excuſe for the Neglect of our Duty; for one Sin cannot be an Excuſe for another, as will appear, if we con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider ſome of thoſe particular Qualifications for this Duty, the want of which makes men unworthy Receivers when they come to it: As firſt, if we conſider the Knowledge of Chriſt and this Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance, the want of which is rather matter of ſhame than an Excuſe for ſtaying away, in that we are ignorant in the midſt of ſuch means and helps to Knowledge. Nay, ſhould Chriſt ask a Man, Why doſt not thou come to the Sacrament? And he anſwers, Becauſe I don't know thee, nor it: would this Excuſe be taken? No, rather it would incenſe Chriſt the more, that he ſhould plead his own Neglects as an Excuſe for Sin, and pretend the want of that to defend him, when 'tis his own Sin and Fault that he wants it.</p>
            <p>And ſo in the want of Deſires after Chriſt, and his Ordinances, it will be no Excuſe for not com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing thereto, that we had no deſire to them or him, but rather an aggravation of our Fault not to deſire him, and therefore to ſtay away from him.</p>
            <p>The like I might ſhew under the want of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance; that to neglect coming to the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment becauſe we don't repent, is to make that which is an Inſtance of our ſad Eſtate, a Reaſon for neglecting a Means of Salvation; yea it is to urge our Folly, and the danger of our Condition as a reaſon for not coming to the Ordinance of Pardon, which tho' we don't come to, yet we ought to perform the other, becauſe it is that which we muſt neceſſarily perform, (if we would be ſaved) whether we receive the Sacrament or not; and therefore if we don't repent, the more inexcuſeable are we, when tho' God Commands it,
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:94102:30"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="49" facs="tcp:94102:30"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="50" facs="tcp:94102:31"/>and we have ſuch need of it, we yet neglect it. The want therefore of that which is neceſſary in order to ſave us, can't be a good Excuſe for neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lecting the means of Salvation; ſo that if we come without Repentance to the Sacrament, we come unworthily; but the more unexcuſeable are we when we do not repent, ſeeing it is ſo neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary, whether we come to the Sacrament, or not.</p>
            <p>Nay even under the want of Charity, it is no Excuſe for not communicating, to ſay, we are not in Charity; for if we are not, what can we ſay for our ſelves why we are not? We are com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded to be in Charity, and there is reaſon for it, whether we receive the Sacrament or not; nay, if we are not yet, the more reaſon have we to be ſo for the future, and ſo come to this Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinance of Charity to have the pardon of our paſt Uncharitableneſs ſeal'd unto us.</p>
            <p>By theſe and the like Inſtances we ſee, That the want of the Qualifications of a Worthy Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municant is no Excuſe for our not receiving the Sacrament, any further than one Sin is an Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſe for another, or the breaking of one Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand is an Apology for the violation of another. The want indeed of doing our Duty in ſome In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances, may render us unfit for it in others; but it is no Excuſe for doing ill in one thing, that we have not done well in another, nor is one Fault a juſt plea for another: For if it ſhould be ſo, it would not only exempt Men from Receiving the Sacrament, but many other Duties of publick Worſhip, and we may as well excuſe our ſelves for not Praying at all, as not Receiving at all; becauſe when we are without the Qualifications of Faith, Repentance, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> we are as unfit to pray
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:94102:31"/>as to receive the Sacrament; which brings me to the latter part of the fourth Head, <hi>Viz.</hi> That the not partaking of other Ordinances worthily, makes men lyable to Damnation, as well as the not partaking of the Sacrament worthily. Thus for inſtance: To pray is an Ordinance of the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel, as well as a Duty, by Natural Religion, and yet to pray unworthily doth not only pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voke God not to hear our Prayers, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 66.18. but <hi>is an abomination to him,</hi> Prov. 15.8. and what is an Abomination to God, I think I need not prove, that it deſerves his Condemnation.</p>
            <p>Nay, As to come without Repentance to the Lord's Supper, ſo to pray without it is exceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing dangerous, becauſe ſuch Men that pray as well as receive without it give God the Lye, and pray in Hypocriſie; nay, without it a Man is an unworthy performer of any Duty, and is always lyable to Damnation, <hi>Luke</hi> 13.3.</p>
            <p>The like I might ſhew in the matter of Faith, That if a Man prays without Faith, he no more prayeth aright than he receives aright without it, <hi>James</hi> 1.6. Nay even in the matter of Charity it is as unworthy dealing with God, and with the Duty of Prayer, to ask the Forgiveneſs of our Sins upon the merits of Chriſt's ſufferings, whilſt we do not forgive men their Treſpaſſes, as it is to deſire it under the Commemoration of his Suf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferings with the ſame Uncharitableneſs; for by begging of Forgiveneſs by vertue of them in Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, we do Commemorate it by words, as in the Sacrament we do it by Signs and viſible Repreſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations.</p>
            <p>And indeed both in the Sacrament and in Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, to ask for Forgiveneſs whilſt we are uncharita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, is but to provoke God, and in both we play
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:94102:32"/>the Hypocrite with God, whilſt we plead Chriſts Sufferings for the removal of the puniſhment, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore we have left the Sin.</p>
            <p>And as in the Inſtance of Prayer, ſo under the Ordinance of Hearing, I might ſhew you that the unworthy performance thereof renders men liable to Damnation; for thus we are told, that unleſs the Word of God be regarded, and have a wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy or due reſpect, it is but a ſavour of Death; 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 2.16. it will riſe up in Judgment againſt us, and by it we ſhall be Condemned, <hi>John</hi> 12.48.</p>
            <p>And yet notwithſtanding the great Danger of Praying or Hearing unworthily, the very Perſons that pretend the fears of Unworthineſs in Receiv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the Sacrament for the Neglect thereof, can by their Actions ſhew, that they may be fit enough for Reading, Hearing, and Praying; and they reckon that through the Mercy of God, and the Merits of Chriſt, they may have reaſon to hope for a favourable acceptance of their Devotion.</p>
            <p>Well now, we may venture upon Prayer to God, and therein to implore the pardon of our Sins upon the Merits of Chriſt's ſufferings: Nay, ſhould we blame any Perſon for a total Neglect of Prayer, (See <hi>Caſe of Doubting Conſcience,</hi> p. 38.) notwithſtanding there is danger in Praying un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthily? And may not we venture too upon the Sacrament? Are not we as worthy to receive the Sacramental Bleſſings as we are to receive the Pardon of Sin, or other Bleſſings deſir'd in Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er? Surely if thrô Mercy we are fit to pray to God, as Chriſtians are to be fit, we are fit to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive his Sacrament: If indeed we do not know what is ſignify'd when we Commemorate Chriſt's Dying Love in the Sacrament; if we have no De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſires
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:94102:32"/>after Chriſt; if we have not Charity, and are without Faith, and are not thankful for God's Love to us in Chriſt, we are not fit to receive, nor to pray as Chriſtians do; for as we ſtate the Notion and Duty of Prayer to Chriſtians, it is as requiſite that we know what we deſire, or have apprehenſions thereof, that we pray in Faith and in Charity, that we have deſires after Chriſt, when we beg an Intereſt in him, and Forgiveneſs thrô him, or the like, as when we beg the par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don of our Sins at the Sacrament; yea when in Prayer we pray to God for pardon for Chriſt's ſake, we are ſuppos'd then to Commemorate his Merits in words, (as in the Sacrament we do by ſigns) tho' a Commemoration in words is not e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough always, becauſe he whoſe Merits we Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>memorate hath oblig'd us ſo to do, by ſigns as well as in words.</p>
            <p>So that if we are ſincere in our words or Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, and we hope that we can put up Prayers in ſuch a way as God will pardon the defects there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, and accept of them through the Vertue of Chriſt's Merits and Interceſſion; I can't ſee but thoſe that are worthy in God's Acceptance to pray as Chriſtians ought to pray, <hi>viz.</hi> in the Name and through the Mediation of Jeſus Chriſt, are alſo worthy in the ſame ſenſe to perform other Religious Duties, and that God is willing to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept of their ſincere Endeavours to Worſhip him in the Sacrament as well as in Prayer, and eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially when he hath Commanded us to receive his Sacraments, as well as to pray to him upon the Merits of his Sufferings, when we are of Age and Underſtanding ſo to do.</p>
            <p>In ſhort, He that is a good Chriſtian, is fit to be a Communicant, and he that is not ſo, is as
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:94102:33"/>unfit to pray as to Communicate. If we live in Sin, we can neither worthily pray nor receive, but whatever Ordinance we meddle with, our ſins debarr us the benefit thereof, as well as provoke God therein; and we can no more be accepted of without Charity in Prayer, than in the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. But on the other hand, if we are ſincere Chriſtians, and would ſerve God in all the parts of his Worſhip and Service as well as we can, and are ſorry for our failures, we are not only of the number of them whoſe Prayers God will be pleas'd to hear, but if we receive the Sacrament may ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perimentally feel thereby our Growth in Grace, and in the Knowledge of our Lord Jeſus. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as on the other hand, to all the forementioned Dangers of a total and wilful Neglect of the Lords Supper, there is alſo this, that by a total and wilful neglect thereof, we may bring our ſelves to a diſuſe of other Ordinances alſo, and not only bring upon our ſelves a Careleſneſs of Spirit in matters of (eſpecially inſtituted) Religion, but fall into a careleſs and looſe way of Living too.</p>
            <p>Its true indeed, that neither the Neglect of Praying, of Hearing and Reading God's Word, nor an ill Life, neceſſarily follow the total Neglect of the Lords Supper, yet ſhould I ſay, that the Looſeneſs of the preſent Age, and the viſible De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cay of Piety amongſt us, is in ſome meaſure owing to the great Neglect, and little ſenſe that too ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny have of the neceſſity and Excellency of this Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance, I believe I ſhould hardly be diſproved: For tho' it will not be allow'd, that the oftner Men receive the Lord's Supper, the more Holy they are, and the leſs they ſin; yet ſince in the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiving of this Ordinance we Commemorate the Sufferings of Chriſt for Sin, (and ſo thereby are
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:94102:33"/>made ſenſible what an Evil and hateful thing it is in God's ſight, when even nothing could expiate for it but the Blood of Chriſt the Son of God,) as alſo are ſuppos'd to renew our Covenant with God, that we will live better for the future; we can't but own that the Sacrament of the Lords Supper is a great Argument if not means againſt Sinning.</p>
            <p>And this not only thoſe who upon the ſenſe of their approach hereto, make ſome formal and temporary ſhews of Repentance and Promiſes to do better, do thereby declare, that it is an Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to leave off Sin, but even thoſe Perſons that Wilfully neglect to receive it, becauſe they are loth to leave their Sins, (which they think they are oblig'd to do, if they ſhould receive this Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament) I ſay, upon this their Reaſon of For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bearance, do they even own, that the receiving of it is an Argument and Obligation againſt Sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning.</p>
            <p>If therefore the Receiving of the Sacrament of the Lord's Supper be ſo great an Argument and Obligation againſt Sin, it follows, that the more wilfully we chooſe to live in the neglect of one, the leſſer help we have againſt the other, and ſo may the more eaſily be brought thereto.</p>
            <p>I do not deny after all, that Perſons who live in a frequent partaking of the Communion, may yet live as looſely as many that live in the Neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect of this Ordinance; but then this is as true, that thoſe who receive this Sacrament, have one Argument and Means more againſt Sinning which the other have not; yea the thing being equally conſider'd, (not to mention thoſe Temporary Acts of Devotion as well as Forbearance from Sin, which many (if not moſt) Men are apt to have
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:94102:34"/>before and upon a Communion day, as alſo the real Change which God is pleas'd to work many times upon ſome men by their attendance upon this Ordinance) I ſay, the thing being equally conſidered, thoſe that come to the Communion out of a ſenſe of Chriſt's Command, and their Du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty ſo to do, are in a more probable way of leaving their Sins, than thoſe are who live in a total and wilful Neglect of it, (eſpecially if the Love to Sin be the Foundation of their Neglect;) and the Reaſon is this, becauſe the one ſort hath one means and help more againſt Sin (if we will al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low that God's Ordinances are ſo) than the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.</p>
            <p>And accordingly I do not find but that many Perſons who frequent this Ordinance, live as un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blameably as thoſe that abſtain from it; and if they do not, they are the more inexcuſable in their Sins, and that becauſe the more frequently they come to it, the further Tye and Obligation do they lay upon themſelves to abſtain from Sin.</p>
            <p>And now perhaps may ſome deſire to be inform'd what they ſhall do in this Caſe: We are ſure (ſay they) if we come to the Sacrament of the Lord's Supper, that we are unworthy; and if we come not, or eſpecially live in a total Neglect thereof, and don't endeavour to fit our ſelves, we are as unworthy and in as dangerous a Condition. To whom I Anſwer, that they are neither to live in a <hi>total</hi> and <hi>wilful</hi> Neglect thereof, nor yet to come unworthily, but to make themſelves ready, and then they may, yea then they ought to come. If any of us remain in Ignorance or in Sin, and do not endeavour to know or live better; the truth is, we are not worthy Communicants if we
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:94102:34"/>come to, nor are we ſafe if we ſtay from this Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinance; there is danger both ways, it being no Excuſe for not receiving, that we live in Ignorance or Sin when we have Means and Calls to do better, and therefore ought to accept and make uſe there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of: And indeed, to live in Ignorance or Sin under Means and Calls to do better, is that which is unjuſtifyable in all People, and ſuch a ſtate as for their Souls good they ought (ſo far as they have opportunity and Ability) to be free from; it being the Duty of all that pretend to Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>anity, at leaſt to know God and his Son Jeſus Chriſt, as alſo to be Regenerate; which if they do, or are, they are not to reckon themſelves un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthy; for ſuch Chriſt invites and receives, and to thoſe that he thus deals with, we are not to deny his Sacraments, nor reckon them unfit for them: And ſuch indeed are all good Chriſtians, <hi>viz.</hi> Perſons invited by him, and theſe are the Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons that I am now perſwading to come to the Sacrament of the Lord's Supper, and not to ſtay away by reaſon of their doubts and fears of their own Unworthineſs, and <hi>ſo</hi> unfitneſs for ſo Sacred an Ordinance.</p>
            <p>For as to Wicked Mens Doubts of their Unfit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, a great deal of reaſon there is for them, whilſt they remain ſo; to ſuch the Sacrament is no more than it was to <hi>Judas,</hi> till God is pleas'd to work a Change upon them; ſuch muſt believe and repent, and then they may come, but not till then; and if they do, it is upon their own pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ril.</p>
            <p>It is therefore to the Conſcientious Perſon that in the cloſe of this Diſcourſe I am going to ſpeak to: To one that fears, and waiteth upon God in his other other Ordinances, but only is hindred
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:94102:35"/>by ſome unhappy Doubts, (unhappy I call them, that hinder a Chriſtian from ſo neceſſary, ſo com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortable an Ordinance) if ſuch an one ſaith he is unworthy for it: I anſwer, it is more than he knows, or more than Chriſt hath told him; and till Chriſt denies a Man his Fellowſhip, he ought not to debar himſelf of it.</p>
            <p>But why art thou unworthy, Oh ſincere Soul, of this Ordinance more than thou art of Prayer? Thou doubt'ſt not to make Prayers, and implore the pardon of thy Sins upon the merits of Chriſt's Sufferings, why ſhould'ſt thou doubt then thank<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully to Commemorate theſe ſufferings in the great Ordinance of their Remembrance? Surely if thou art permitted to offer up thy Prayers upon the Merits of Chriſt's Sufferings, thou may'ſt as well be permitted to offer them up upon the Memori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al thereof; if thou haſt but the Knowledge of the Nature and End of the Sacrament; if thou deſireſt Chriſt, and the Ways of Communion with him; if thou art in Charity with God and the World, and endeavour'ſt to live well; if thou believeſt, and art thankful, who forbids thee the Sacrament? Doth the Goſpel, or Chriſt? or doth his Church? No Verily: For pity ſake therefore don't make thy ſelf more unworthy than thou art: Don't Complement away the bleſſing of this Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinance, by pretneding thy unfitneſs, ſo long as thou lead'ſt the Life of a Chriſtian: Do but try, and come with the Qualifications afore-mention'd, or with a ſincere endeavour ſo to do, and then tell me whether Chriſt will caſt thee out. Nay, if thou hopeſt to be pardoned by Chriſt, to be ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved by the Benefits of his Paſſion, thou need'ſt not to fear that which he hath appointed as the great means of conveyance of ſuch Benefits to Believers,
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:94102:35"/>nor need'ſt thou dread the Ordinance of Chriſt, when thou ſtedfaſtly believeſt thy Intereſt in him; for if thou art worthy in Chriſt's ſight to partake of the Redemption purchas'd by him, thou may'ſt depend upon it, thou art not to be debarr'd the Seals thereof.</p>
            <p>Ay, but may ſome ſtill urge, That tho' they come with the Qualifications aforeſaid, tho' they ſincerely ſeek to prepare themſelves, yet ſtill they find themſelves, or at leaſt judge themſelves un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthy of this Ordinance; becauſe when they do come to it, they find that as they have many times unwilling dulneſſes and diſtractions of Spirit in this as well as other Duties, ſo at beſt they are wanting in thoſe tranſports and extraordinary Acts of Joy and Complacency both at, and after the Sacrament, which they many times diſcern, or believe to be in others.</p>
            <p>To whom I Anſwer, That the want thereof doth not make Men Unworthy Communicants, it being not neceſſary that all Chriſtians ſhould be ſo enliven'd, God neither having made a Promiſe, nor commanded it as a Duty, that all Communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cants ſhould be ſo endowed.</p>
            <p>I do not deny but God may give ſometimes to ſome Perſons theſe Extraordinary Impulſes and Conſolation; and I do believe that many there are who are able to ſpeak great things of their Faith in, and Communion with Chriſt; yea, ſuch Complacency as well as Extraordinary Acts of Love and Adoration do they ſhew therein, that one would imagine that their Souls were carry'd up to Heaven, and that with St. <hi>Stephen,</hi> they were not only viewing their Saviour by Faith in Figure and Sacrament, but by perſonal ſight, yea by their Geſtures and by their Words, which moſt
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:94102:36"/>ſweetly ſet forth Chriſt's Love to them, and theirs to Chriſt, we may be apt to believe, that if they had not been in Heaven, yet they minded nothing elſe, and were going up to be for ever with the Lord.</p>
            <p>But however we may admire this in others, we are not to judge thoſe as unworthy, that can't reach thereto; for if we ſhould ſo judge, we ſhould not only condemn a great part of the Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neration of God's Children, but ſhou'd caſt a ſtumbling-block before them, and render their Caſe worſe than it is: For as the ſaving Influences and Operations of God's Spirit may be where there wants theſe Extraordinary Impulſes and Conſola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, ſo a Man may receive the Sacrament to very good purpoſes without them, there being many good Men that by Means of the bleſſings of the Sacrament are ſtrengthen'd more in the Spirit, that are more conſirm'd in their Faith, in their Love to Chriſt, and hearty deſire of Thankfulneſs and Obedience, that yet do not arrive to thoſe paſſionate heats and flights as others do.</p>
            <p>I think I need not tell you, that with many, if not moſt good Chriſtians, it is in Holy Duties as it was with the Diſciples of Chriſt in the time of his Agony: tho' their <hi>Spirits</hi> may be willing to ſerve and adore Chriſt in the higheſt manner, yet <hi>their fleſh is weak; Mat.</hi> 26.40, 41. and tho' they don't allow themſelves therein, yet they find them ſelves apt to ſtart aſide, or tyre when their Hearts are lifted up to God; and they can hardly watch and pray one hour, but ſomething or other, either from themſelves, or the preſence of ſome Worldly Object, is apt to give ſome diverſion or diſtracti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to them in their moſt ſolemn Acts of Devotion and Worſhip.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="61" facs="tcp:94102:36"/>
And yet after all, theſe very Perſons may not only have an high eſteem of Chriſt, and a real Love to him and his Service, but would be gl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d that they could ſerve him better: And now <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> to be ſuppos'd, that God will judge them unwor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy, who ſerve him in Sincerity of Heart, and are ſorry that they can't Worſhip him ſo much as they ſhou'd? No ſurely, Chriſt that bore with the Infirmities of his Diſciples, that knows our Frame and Conſtitution, that remembers we are but Men, will not be extream to mark what we unwillingly do amiſs, but <hi>as a Father piti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>th his Children, ſo doth he pity them that fear him; Pſal.</hi> 103.13. that ſet their Hearts to wait upon their Saviour in Ways of his own Appointment, tho' they can't Worſhip him in that perfect and cheer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful way as ſome do, ſincerity of Heart going a great way to God's Acceptance of our Endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vours, as well as to the pardon of our unwilling, and repented of Infirmities.</p>
            <p>And indeed herein is matter of Comfort, th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> God accepts of men according to the ſincerity o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> their Hearts and Endeavours, rather than by the Tyde or heat of Mens Affections, which is higher in ſome than in others, even upon Natural as <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> as Religions Agitations, nay, is higher in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> ſame men at one time, than at another: And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, tho' we can't approach to, or come <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> from the Sacrament with thoſe paſſionate Tr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ports of Love and Conſolation as ſome M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> or as we could wiſh; yet if what we <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> ſenſible Joys, we make up in Truth and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> let us not diſtruſt but God will have <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> on us, and deal with us according to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> would, and endeavour to be, and not by what <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> are, <hi>viz.</hi> Perſons of Infirmities <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> were Angels, Go<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> expect <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="60" facs="tcp:94102:37"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="61" facs="tcp:94102:37"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="62" facs="tcp:94102:38"/>Angels from us; but as he knows we are but Men, ſo he requires no more than the ſervice of Men, who do they what they can, have their In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmities and Failures ſometimes, and whoſe Fleſh hath its weakneſſes, be their Spirits never ſo wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling.</p>
            <p>And tho' indeed where God gives it to Men to be fill'd with ſuch Extraordinary Conſolation, and Efforts of Devotion, they are not to hinder or reſtrain the flowings thereof; yet where God is not pleas'd to beſtow them, as Men ought not to murmur againſt God, ſo not to condemn them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves as unworthy, becauſe they are without them. Theſe being Arbitrarious Gifts, which God giveth as he ſeeth good, and therefore it being not for us to chooſe our places and parts at this Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly Feaſt, we may reckon it ſufficient for us that he gives us his Cup to drink, and that we are qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lify'd and enabled to partake thereof with the ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerity of a Chriſtian, and other neceſſary Qualifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cations.</p>
            <p>If therefore, I ſay, out of a ſenſe of our Duty to God, we come to the Sacrament, and endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour to prepare our ſelves for, and behave our ſelves at it according to the beſt of our Capaci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties and Opportunities, and are ſorry for our fai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lures, we are not to ſtay away from it, though we cannot thereby ſatisfie all the Deſires of our Souls, to be and do as others, God making it our Duty to receive, and that as well as we can, but not to forbear it, becauſe we attain not to thoſe ſenſible Joys and Exaltations of Spirit, as God for Reaſons known to himſelf may impart to others, it being enough for us to make us Communicants, and that with his Bleſſing too, when he beſtows upon us the Graces of his Spirit, and enables us live as Chriſtians.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="63" facs="tcp:94102:38"/>
But yet, if after all I have ſaid in this Matter, the Good, the Religious Soul is yet afraid of the Sacrament, I muſt leave him to the Grace and Mercy of God; which tho' I do not deny him in his Abſence from the Lord's Supper, yet I muſt tell him, that his ſear hinders him the enjoyment of a very comfortable Ordinance to Pious Souls: Nay, his fear (if it is only a ſnare to keep him from coming to, but doth not put him upon a ſerious and hearty endeavour of ſitting him for this Du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, as well as ſeeking for Advice how to remove ſuch fear) doth give too ſhrewd a ſign of his de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cay in Grace. However, let his fears be as un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>willing as can be ſuppos'd, yet they hinder him of an Ordinance, which is not only a great Means and Reaſon for living better, when to all other Helps he hath that of the Sacrament, but alſo of that which is a publick Memorial of Chriſt's Love to Sinners, and is the Communion of the very Body and Blood of Chriſt, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 10.16. as alſo a Means of encreaſing our Union and ſweet Intercourſes with Chriſt.</p>
            <p>And thus have I done with the ſeveral things that I propos'd to be treated of from the words of the Text, and in the cloſe thereof ſhewn, that the ſaying we are unworthy of the Sacrament, doth not make us unworthy; nor are we to ſtay away as unworthy, becauſe we do not arrive to thoſe Tranſports, or Extraordinary Acts of Joy and Complacency, both at, and after the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, which we diſcern or believe to be be in o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, if ſo be we are ſincere, and conſcientiouſly endeavour to do what is requir'd of us.</p>
            <p>Yea of the whole Diſcourſe this is the ſumm, That tho' it be very dangerous to receive the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament of the Lord's Supper unworthily, upon thoſe Accounts, or by thoſe Ways that Men may
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:94102:39"/>be ſaid to receive it unworthily, in that ſo to do, makes us lyable to Damnation, both Temporal and Eternal, without Repentance, yet a <hi>total</hi> and <hi>wilful</hi> Neglect thereof is a dealing with it as un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthily, which Chriſtians ſhould fear ſo to Neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect, as well as to receive unworthily.</p>
            <p>And now what remains, but that I conclude with a word or two to my Pariſhioners, for whoſe ſake chiefly I have publiſh'd this Diſcourſe: You have heard of the benefits of the Ordinance of the Lord's Supper by my Mouth, and have been told thereof in God's Word, and therefore cannot ſay it is in vain to come to it: You have heard, that Chriſt commands the receiving of it as a Du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, and therefore can't ſay it is unneceſſary: You have heard what are the Qualifications, even no other but what are neceſſary to make your Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers accepted, and prove your ſelves to be good Chriſtians: And now ſince you hope you are Chriſtians, and hope for Pardon and Salvation by Chriſt, why ſhould you be afraid of a Chriſtian Duty? Or to partake of that which is the means or Seal of Pardon? Nay, why ſhould ye be un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>willing, as I fear too many amongſt you are, not ſo much becauſe ye may not receive, but be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe ye will not prepare your ſelves for it?</p>
            <p>And now if after all the frequent Exhortations to prepare your ſelves, and to come to this Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinance, you yet live in a total and wilful Neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect of ſo Sacred and ſo uſeful an Ordinance, you can't ſay, if evil befalls you for this Neglect, that your perſiſting therein hath been occaſion'd by my Negligence in warning you: For as I call Heaven and Earth to witneſs, ſo I appeal to your ſelves, whether I have not admoniſh'd you of the illneſs and danger of a <hi>total</hi> and <hi>wilful</hi> Neglect, as well as of an unworthy Receiving of the Lord's Supper.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="65" facs="tcp:94102:39"/>
But, Oh Bleſſed Jeſus, thou that giveſt us ſuch Spiritual Food, give us at length right Appetites to it; Thou that haſt Inſtituted this Ordinance, fit us alſo for it, Create in our Hearts ſuch Holy Deſires to thee, that we may be glad of ſuch op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunities of Union and Communion with thee; till from enjoying thee in thy Ordinances, we are made Eternally worthy by thee to enjoy thy preſence and the Bleſſings thereof in Heaven; which that we may all be, God of his Infinite Mercy grant to us all, through the Merits of Chriſt Jeſus. To whom, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="publishers_advertisement">
            <pb n="66" facs="tcp:94102:40"/>
            <head>
               <hi>Books lately Printed for, and Sold by</hi> Thomas Parkhurſt, <hi>at the</hi> Bible <hi>and</hi> Three Crowns <hi>at the lower end of</hi> Cheapſide, <hi>near</hi> Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers Chappel.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>SYnodicon in Gallia Reformata:</hi> Or, the Acts, De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſions, Decrees and Canons of thoſe Famous National Councils of the Reformed Churches in <hi>France,</hi> being a moſt Faithful and Impartial Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtory of the Riſe, Growth, Perfection, Decay of the Reformation in that Kingdom, with its fatal Cataſtrophe upon the Revocation of the Edict at <hi>Nants</hi> in the Year 1685. alſo the Confeſſion of Faith and Diſcipline of thoſe Churches, their Speeches, Sacred Politicks, Caſes of Conſcience, and Controverſies in Divinity, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> their Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, Laws, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Collected out of the Original Manuſcript-Acts of thoſe Renowned Synods. In two Vol. Fol. By <hi>John Quick.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A Body of Practical Divinity, conſiſting of a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove 176 Sermons on the leſſer Catechiſm, Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed by the Reverend Aſſembly of Divines at <hi>Weſtminſter,</hi> with a Supplement of ſome Sermons on ſeveral Texts of Scripture. By <hi>Thomas Watſon,</hi> formerly Miniſter of St. <hi>Stephen</hi>'s <hi>Walbrook, Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don.</hi> Recommended by ſeveral Miniſters to Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters of Families and others. In Folio.</p>
            <p>Theological Diſcourſes and Sermons on ſeveral Occaſions. In two Parts. By <hi>John Wallis.</hi> D. D. Profeſſor of Geometry in <hi>Oxford.</hi> Quarto.</p>
            <p>A Brief Tract on the Fourth Commandment, wherein is ſhown the Cauſe of all our Controver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſies
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:94102:40"/>about the Sabbath-day, and the means of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conciling them. Recommended by the Reverend Dr. <hi>Bates</hi> and Mr. <hi>John Howe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A Sermon Preached before the King and Queen at <hi>Whitehall, Nov.</hi> 5. 1692. By <hi>Richard</hi> Lord Biſhop of <hi>Bath</hi> and <hi>Wells.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Death Improved, and Immoderate Sorrow for Deceaſed Friends and Relations Reproved. By <hi>Edward Bury,</hi> formerly Miniſter of <hi>Great Bolas</hi> in <hi>Shropſhire. Octavo.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A Paraphraſe on the Pſalms of <hi>David</hi> in Metre. By the the late Reverend Mr. <hi>Richard Baxter.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A Diſcourſe of Earthquakes, as they are Super<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>natural and premonitory ſigns to a Nation, with a reſpect to what hath Occurred in this Year 1692. and ſome ſpecial Reflections thereupon: As alſo on that Security and Aſſurance of Mind which is attainable in the light and Power of Religion un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the greateſt ſurprizals and terrors of ſenſe, with ſome Enquiry upon the gaounds both of our Fears and Hopes, as to the Publick State of the Church of Chriſt in this Day.</p>
            <p>The Confirming Work of Religion, or its great things made plain by their primary Evidences and Demonſtrations, whereby the meaneſt in the Church may ſoon be made able to render a ſolid and rational Account of the Faith. Theſe two laſt by <hi>Rob. Fleming</hi> Author of <hi>The Fulfilling of the Scriptures,</hi> and Miniſter in <hi>Rotterdam.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Advice to an Only Child, or Excellent Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſel to all Young Perſons: Containing the ſumm and ſubſtance of Experimental and Practical Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinity. Written by an Eminent and Judicious Divine, for the Private Uſe of an Only Child, now made Publick for the benefit of all.</p>
            <p>The Carnality of Religious Conrention, in two Sermons Preached at the <hi>Merchants Lecture</hi> in <hi>Broad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtreet,</hi> by the Reverend Mr. <hi>John Howe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="68" facs="tcp:94102:41"/>
A Short Story of the Riſe, Reign and Ruin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> of the <hi>Antinomians,</hi> Familiſts and Libertines that infected the Churches in <hi>New-England.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Scotch Pſalms in Metre, recommended by 26 famous Divines, lately Rprinted in 12<hi rend="sup">o</hi>.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="publishers_advertisement">
            <head>
               <hi>Books Printed for</hi> Obed. Smith, <hi>Bookſeller i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> Daventry <hi>in</hi> Northamptonſhire.</head>
            <p>WOrds to give to the Young Man Know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge and Diſcretion, or the Law of Kindneſs in the Tongue of a Father to his Son.</p>
            <p>A Treatiſe of Faith and Repentance, with a Diſcourſe of Self-denyal.</p>
            <p>A Treatiſe of Grace and Duty.</p>
            <p>Some Rules to uſe the World, ſo as not to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buſe either it or our ſelves. All by <hi>Francis Fuller,</hi> M. A.</p>
            <p>Holy Breathings under the ſenſe of Sin, toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with a Soveraign Preparative towards a bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed Eternity. By <hi>Tho. Price.</hi> The <hi>2d.</hi> Edit.</p>
            <p>The Life and Death of <hi>James Arminius,</hi> and <hi>Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Epiſcopius,</hi> Profeſſors of Divinity in the Uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſity of <hi>Leyden</hi> in <hi>Holland;</hi> both of them famous Defenders of the Doctrine of Gods Univerſal Grace, and Sufferers for it, now publiſhed in the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Tongue.</p>
            <pb n="60" facs="tcp:94102:42"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="61" facs="tcp:94102:42"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="62" facs="tcp:94102:43"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="63" facs="tcp:94102:43"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
